<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A seasonable, legall, and historicall vindication and chronologicall collection of the good, old, fundamentall, liberties, franchises, rights, laws of all English freemen (their best inheritance, birthright, security, against arbitrary, tyrannicall, and Egyptian burdens) and of their strenuous defence in all former ages; of late years most dangerously undermined, and almost totally subverted, under the specious disguise of their defence and future establishment, upon a sure basis, their pretended, greatest propugners. Wherein is irrefragably evinced by Parliamentary records, proofs, presidents, that we have such fundamentall liberties, ... that to attempt or effect the subversion of all or any of them, ... is high treason: ... / By William Prynne of Swainswick, Esquire.</title>
            <title>Seasonable, legall, and historicall vindication and chronologicall collection of the good, old, fundamentall, liberties, franchises, rights, laws of all English freemen. Part 1</title>
            <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E812_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207634</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866673</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866673</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118951</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91263)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118951)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 123:E812[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A seasonable, legall, and historicall vindication and chronologicall collection of the good, old, fundamentall, liberties, franchises, rights, laws of all English freemen (their best inheritance, birthright, security, against arbitrary, tyrannicall, and Egyptian burdens) and of their strenuous defence in all former ages; of late years most dangerously undermined, and almost totally subverted, under the specious disguise of their defence and future establishment, upon a sure basis, their pretended, greatest propugners. Wherein is irrefragably evinced by Parliamentary records, proofs, presidents, that we have such fundamentall liberties, ... that to attempt or effect the subversion of all or any of them, ... is high treason: ... / By William Prynne of Swainswick, Esquire.</title>
                  <title>Seasonable, legall, and historicall vindication and chronologicall collection of the good, old, fundamentall, liberties, franchises, rights, laws of all English freemen. Part 1</title>
                  <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the authour, and are to be sold by Edward Thomas in Green Arbour,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Second and third parts were published in 1655 and 1657.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7ber [i.e., September] 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Constitutional history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118951:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A
SEASONABLE, LEGALL,
AND
HISTORICALL VINDICATION
AND
<hi>Chronologicall COLLECTION</hi> of the Good, Old, Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall,
<hi>Liberties, Franchiſes, Rights, Laws of all Engliſh Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>
(their beſt <hi>Inheritance, Birthright, Security,</hi> againſt
<hi>Arbitrary, Tyrannicall, and</hi> Egyptian <hi>Burdens</hi>) and of their <hi>ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous
Defence in all former Ages;</hi> of late years moſt <hi>dangerouſly
undermined, and almoſt totally ſubverted,</hi> under the ſpecious
<hi>Diſguiſe</hi> of their <hi>Defence</hi> and <hi>future Establiſhment,</hi> upon a <hi>Sure
Baſis,</hi> their Pretended, <hi>Greateſt Propugners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is
Irrefragably evinced by <hi>Parliamentary Records, Proofs, Preſidents,
That we have ſuch</hi> Fundamentall <hi>Liberties, Franchiſes, Rights, Laws, That
to attempt or effect the Subverſion of all or any of them, (or of our Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall
Government) by Fraud or Force,</hi> is <hi>High Treaſon:</hi> The principall of
them ſummed up in <hi>9 Propoſitions:</hi> The chief printed <hi>Treatiſes</hi> aſſerting them,
ſpecified: <hi>A Chronologicall History of our Anceſtors zeal, vigilancy, courage,
prudence, in gaining, regaining, enlarging, defending, oft confirming, and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuating
them to posterity,</hi> by <hi>Great Charters,</hi> Statutes, New <hi>Confirmations, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications,
Speciall Conſervators, Conſultations, Petitions, Declarations,
Remonstrances, Oaths, Proteſtations, Vows, Leagues, Covenants,</hi> and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
by their <hi>Arms,</hi> when neceſſitated during all the <hi>Britons, Saxons, Danes,
Normans</hi> and <hi>Engliſh Kings</hi> Reigns, till this preſent; collected for preſent
and future publick benefit: With a Brief Touch of their late <hi>unparalelled
Infringements</hi> and <hi>Subverſions</hi> in every particular: The <hi>Triall of all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors</hi>
by their <hi>Peers,</hi> and <hi>Juries,</hi> juſtified, as the onely <hi>legal, beſt,</hi> moſt <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different;</hi>
and all other late arbitrary Judicatories, erected for their Triall, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded,
<hi>deſtructive both to our Fundamentall Laws and Liberties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Collected, recommended to the whole <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> as the beſt <hi>Legacy,</hi> he
can leave them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> William Prynne <hi>of</hi> Swainſwick, <hi>Eſquire.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>Pſalm 11. 3.</bibl>
            <q>If the <hi>Foundations</hi> be deſtroyed, what can the righteous do?</q>
            <bibl>Pſalm 82 5.</bibl>
            <q>They know not, neither will they underſtand, they walk on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <bibl>Dan. 7. 24 25, 26.</bibl>
            <q>And another ſhall ariſe after the Kings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed for the Authour, and are to be ſold by <hi>Edward
Thomas</hi> in <hi>Green Arbour,</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="vindication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118951:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118951:2"/>
            <head>A Seaſonable, Hiſtorical, Legal,
VINDICATION,
AND
CHRONOLOGICAL COLLECTION</head>
            <head type="sub">Of the good Old Fundamental Liberties,
Franchiſes, Rights, Laws, of all Engliſh Freemen;
(their beſt Inheritance, Birth-right, Security, againſt
Arbitrary Tyranny, Egyptian Slavery and Burdens)
of late yeers moſt dangerouſly undermined, oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
and almost totally ſubverted, under the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
feigned Diſguiſe of their Defence, Enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and future Eſtabliſhment upon a ſure Baſis.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an univerſal received</hi> Principle,
<hi>and</hi> experimental Truth, <hi>beyond all
contradiction,</hi> That no natural ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,
no artificial Building, no Civil
or Eccleſiaſtical Corporation, Realm,
Reipublike, Government, or Society of
men; no Art nor Science whatſoever,
can poſſibly be erected, ſupported, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed,
preſerved, or continued in their
being or well-being, without <hi>FOUNDATIONS; whereon
as they were at firſt</hi> erected, <hi>ſo they muſt neceſſarily ſtill</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118951:3"/>
depend, <hi>or elſe they will preſently fall to</hi> utter ruine.</p>
            <p>Hence it is, (to wave all Humane Authorities in ſo clear
a Verity) that in God's own ſacred unerring<note n="a" place="margin">Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 17. 17. 2 Cor. 6. 7. Eph. 1. 13. Jam. 1. 18</note> 
               <hi>Word of
Truth,</hi> we find frequent mention of the natural<note n="b" place="margin">2 Sam. 22. 8, 16. Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 38. 4, 6. Pſal 18. 15 <hi>&amp; 102. 25. &amp;</hi> 104. 5. Prov. 8. 29 Iſa. 24. 18. <hi>&amp; 40. 21. &amp; 48. 13. &amp;</hi> 51. 13, 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. 31. 17. Zech. 12 1. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca. 1. 6. Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 17. 24. Epheſ. 4. 4. Heb. 1. 10. <hi>&amp; 4. 3. &amp;</hi> 9 26. 1 Pet. 1 20.</note> 
               <hi>FOUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DATIONS</hi>
of the vaſt natural Fabrick of the Earth, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,
and World it ſelf; of the Artificial Material<note n="c" place="margin">1 King. 5. 17. <hi>&amp; 6. 37. &amp;</hi> 7. 9, 10. Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4. 13 <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. 3. Pſa. 137 7. Ezek. 41. 8. Hag. 2. 8. Zech. 4 9 <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. 9. Mat. 7. 26, 27. Luke 6 48, 49.</note> 
               <hi>FOUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DATIONS</hi>
of the <hi>material Temple,</hi> walls, <hi>City; of Gods own</hi>
moſt famous city <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and of private houſes: of the
Spiritual<note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 28. 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 54. 11. Pſal. 87. 1. 1 Cor. 3. 10, 11, 12. Heb. 11. 10. 1 Pet. 2. 6. Rev. 21. 14, 19.</note> 
               <hi>FOUNDATION</hi> of the <hi>Spiritual Temple, City
Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>whole Church of God;</hi> even <hi>Jeſus Christ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:</hi>
of the Doctrinal<note n="e" place="margin">2 Tim 1. 19. Heb. 6 1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>FOUNDATIONS,</hi> and <hi>firſt
Principles of Religion, Chriſtianity, Salvation:</hi> yea, of the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical
<note n="f" place="margin">Jer. 50. 15. Micah 1. 6, 7. Luke 6. 48, 49. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 7. 26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>FOUNDATIONS</hi> of <hi>Kingdoms, Reipublikes, Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
Governments, States:</hi> which being once ſhaken, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined,
ſubverted, razed, or deſtroyed, bring unavoidable
ruine and deſolation upon them, (<hi>Pſal. 11. 3. Pſal.</hi> 82. 5, 6.
<hi>Jer.</hi> 50. 17. &amp; 51. 15, 16. <hi>Mic.</hi> 1. 6, 7, 9.) even as we daily
ſee <hi>Caſtles, Walls, Houſes,</hi> to fall inſtantly to the ground, and
become an heap of Confuſion, when their <hi>Foundations</hi> are
blown up, decayed, or demoliſhed.</p>
            <p>Upon which conſideration, thoſe <hi>Publike Laws,</hi> which
eſtabliſh, fence, fortifie, ſupport the <hi>Fundamental</hi> Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions,
Rights, Liberties, Priviledges, of any Nation,
Kingdom, Reipublike, (eſſential to their <hi>being</hi> and <hi>ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi>
as a <hi>free</hi> or <hi>happie</hi> people, againſt the <hi>Invaſions, Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minings,
Encroachments,</hi> of any <hi>Tyrants, Uſurpers, O preſſors,</hi>
or <hi>publike Enemies,</hi> are uſually ſtiled FUNDAMENTAL
LAWS; and have ever been reputed ſo <hi>ſacred, inviolable,
immutable,</hi> in all ages, upon any Pretences of <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> or
<hi>Publike Safety,</hi> that moſt Nations, and our own <hi>Engliſh
Anceſtors,</hi> above others, have freely choſen to hazard, yea
loſe their <hi>Eſtates, Lives,</hi> in their <hi>just defence,</hi> againſt ſuch
exorbitant <hi>Tyrannical Kings,</hi> and other <hi>Powers,</hi> who by
<hi>force</hi> or <hi>policie</hi> have endeavoured to <hi>violate, alter,</hi> or <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert</hi>
them, rather then out of <hi>Cowardize, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhneſs, Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs,</hi>
or want of cordial <hi>love</hi> to the Publike, to ſuffer the
leaſt <hi>infringement, repeal,</hi> or <hi>alteration</hi> of them, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralling
of Themſelves, or their Poſterities, to the <hi>arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118951:3"/>
Wills</hi> of ſuch <hi>Domineering Tyrants,</hi> and <hi>Uſurping
Powers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now becauſe, after all our <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New</hi> (many yeers)
bloody, coſtly, dangerous <hi>Contests</hi> and <hi>Wars,</hi> for the <hi>main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance</hi>
of our <hi>Good Old Fundamental Liberties, Laws, Rights,
Priviledges,</hi> againſt all ſecret or open <hi>underminers</hi> of them,
I clearly behold, with grief of heart, that there is a <hi>ſtrange
monſtrous Generation of New TYRANNICAL STATE-HERETICKS</hi>
ſprung up among us; who are grown ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately
impudent, as not onely to <hi>write,</hi> but publikely to
<hi>aſſert in Print,</hi> (in<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lilb.</hi> tryed and cast, <hi>p.</hi> 39, 40, 142, to 148. 154. <hi>J. Canne's</hi> Voice from the Temple, which perſwades the ſubverſion and aboliſhing of all former Laws, eſpecially for Tythes &amp; Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſupport.</note> 
               <hi>Books</hi> printed by AUTHORITY,
even in <hi>Capitals</hi> in the very <hi>Title-page) That the Free-men
and People of England have no ſuch unalterable Fundamental
Laws and Liberties left them by their forefathers,</hi> (as our <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors</hi>
heretofore conteſted for, both in the Field and
Parliament-Houſe, with <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, <hi>Henry</hi> the
firſt, King <hi>John, Henry</hi> the third, <hi>Edward 1, 2, 3. Richard</hi>
the ſecond, with other Kings and Princes; and our late
<hi>Parliaments</hi> and <hi>Armies</hi> too, with King <hi>James,</hi> and King
<hi>Charles.) That neither</hi> Magna Charta, <hi>nor the</hi> Petition of
Right, <hi>nor the Laws for trying malefactors by Juries of their
peers, are Fundamental, or unalterable; but that the</hi> STATE-PHYSITIANS
(or rather Mountebanks) <hi>of our time, (who
are not tied up to them, but left free unto themſelves) may lay
them quite aſide, either in part or whole, as they ſee cauſe:</hi> Yea,
(having now attained to ſuch a ſuper-tranſcendent Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
as) may (as they aſſert) LAY ASIDE ALL PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAMENTS
and PARLIAMENTARY WAYS, <hi>and
appoint SOMETHING ELSE, as more ſeaſonable and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
to us, and as Providence makes way for it, if they ſee it
more conducing to the ſafety and good of the Commonwealth,</hi>
(that is, to their own private Intereſts, Honours, Profits,
Securities, Deſignes, Oppreſſions, Rapines, gilded over
with this ſpecious pretext.) And then peremptorily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
<hi>That to plead for theſe and ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Fundamental Laws and
L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>berties, as unalterable,</hi> (though the onely Bulwarks and
Badges of our Freedom) <hi>is nothing elſe but to enſlave the
Nation: for by ſuch a Principle, People do not onely loſe their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118951:4"/>
Liberty, but are brought under ſuch a kinde of Tyranny, out
of which (AS BEING WORSE THEN THE AEGYP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIAN
BONDAGE) there is no hope of deliverance.</hi> An
abſurd Tyrannical Paradox, tranſcending any I ever yet
met with in any Author; ſtripping us naked of all our
long-enjoyed Laws, Liberties, Franchiſes, Great Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
at once; tending onely to reduce, and perpetually
inthral us under ſuch an abſolute AEGYPTIAN BON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAGE
and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> without any hope of future delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
from it, which ſome now endeavour to <hi>enta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> on us
and our poſterities for ever, by an <hi>Iron Law,</hi> and <hi>Yoke of
Steel,</hi> in ſtead of reſtoring to us that <hi>Glorious Freedom,</hi>
which we have ſo long expected from them in vain.</p>
            <p>And becauſe I finde the Generality of the <hi>Nobility,
Gentry, Clergie, Commonalty,</hi> of our Nation, after all their
late yeers <hi>expenſive bloody wars,</hi> and <hi>Parliamentary Diſputes,</hi>
for the defence and preſervation of theſe our Ancient He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary
Fundamental Charters, Laws, Liberties, Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,
ſo ſtrangely degenerated both from themſelves,
and their <hi>Heroick prudent Ancestors,</hi> as that they are
more readily inclined, upon every occaſion, out of a baſe,
un-Chriſtian, unmanly, un-Engliſh <hi>fear,</hi> or ſottiſh <hi>cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice</hi>
and <hi>ſtupidity,</hi> wittingly to deſert, betray, ſurrender
them all up into the hands of any <hi>invading Uſurpers,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
the leaſt Publike Claim, Diſſertation, Defence, or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute;
then diligently or couragiouſly to contend for them,
as of late they did: So as that which <hi>Paul</hi> once taxed in
the ſlaviſh beſotted <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 2 Epiſt. 11. 20. may be
moſt truly averred of our <hi>degenerated, inſatuated,</hi> Engliſh
Nation: <hi>Ye ſuffer if a man bring you into bondage, if a man
devour you, if a man take of you, if a man exalt himſelf,</hi> (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
your Laws, Liberties, Franchiſes, Parliaments, Kings,
Nobles, Properties, Lives, Conſciences, and<note n="a" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>all that is
called God, or worſhipped) if a man ſmite you on the face;</hi>
notwithſtanding all their manifold late<note n="b" place="margin">See Exact collect. and a general Collect. of all Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Protestations,
Vows, Covenants, Remonſtrances, Declarations,</hi> and <hi>Publike
Engagements,</hi> to the contrary. And withal, after diligent
enquiry, diſcovering ſcarce one man of <hi>Eminencie</hi> or <hi>Power</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118951:4"/>
in the Nation, nor ſo much as one of my <hi>degenerated tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porizing</hi>
Profeſſion of the <hi>Law,</hi> (even when the<note n="c" place="margin">See Culpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r's <hi>&amp;</hi> Lilly's <hi>Merlins &amp; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manacks,</hi> John Can'<hi>s 2 Voice,</hi> Lilb. <hi>tried and caſt; with many Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itions and Pamphlets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law and Lawyers. The Order of</hi> Aug. 19. 1653. That there ſhould be a Committee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of A NEW BODY of the Law, for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</note> 
               <hi>whole
Body</hi> of our Laws, and all its <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> are <hi>violently aſſault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi>
and devoted unto ſudden ruine, by many <hi>lawleſs ſpirits</hi>)
who hath ſo much Courage, Magnanimity, Honeſty, Zeal,
or cordial Love to his native Country, remaining in his
breſt, as manfully to appear in Publike, for the <hi>ſtrenuous
neceſſary defence</hi> of theſe our <hi>Hereditary, Fundamental Laws,
Liberties, Rights, Franchiſes,</hi> (though their own, and every
other <hi>Engliſh Freeman</hi>'s beſt <hi>Inheritance</hi> and <hi>Security</hi>) for
fear of being perſecuted, impriſoned, cloſe impriſoned,
exiled, condemned, deſtroyed, as a Traytor, Rebel, Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
perſon, Enemy to the Publike, or diſturber of the
Kingdoms Peace, by thoſe who are truely ſuch: I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
conceived, I could not undertake or perform a more
neceſſary, ſeaſonable, beneficial Service for my Country,
(and not to be like thoſe, who are aſhamed, afraid, for the
moſt part, to own, viſit, or be ſeen in the company of thoſe
<hi>Gallant men,</hi> much leſs to aſſiſt, defend, and ſtick cloſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
them in their <hi>dangers,</hi> according to the ſixth Article of
their late <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> who have ſuffered,
acted, and ſtood up moſt for their <hi>Common Liberties, Rights,
Freedoms, Religion,</hi> againſt all invading Tyrants, to their
great diſcouragement and betraying) nor pitch upon any
Subject more proper for me, either as a <hi>common Lawyer,</hi> or
as a <hi>conſtant Advocate</hi> and <hi>Sufferer for the Publike Cauſe,</hi> and
<hi>Liberties of the Nation,</hi> as well under our late extravagant
<hi>Free-State,</hi> as former <hi>Regal</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopal arbitrary Tyranny,</hi>
then in this juncture of our publike affairs, to preſent our
whole diſtracted unſetled <hi>Kingdom</hi> with <hi>An Hiſtorical and
Legal Vindication, and Chronological Collection,</hi> in all Ages,
of theſe Ancient Hereditary <hi>Liberties, Franchiſes,
Rights, Conteſts, Laws, Charters, Records, Monuments</hi> of
former and late times, for their <hi>Confirmation,</hi> and <hi>inviolable
Obſervation,</hi> which our <hi>Anceſtors</hi> and our <hi>Selves</hi> have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
hitherto reputed FUNDAMENTAL, UNALTER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ABLE,
INVIOLABLE, upon any pretext; and have moſt
<hi>eagerly contended for,</hi> with the prodigal expence of many
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118951:5"/>
               <hi>millions</hi> of <hi>Treaſure,</hi> and <hi>whole oceans</hi> of gallant <hi>Christian
Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if, upon the ſerious peruſal of them, the <hi>univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi>
of our <hi>degenerated Nation,</hi> after their many late ſolemn
<hi>Proteſtations, Vows, Leagues, Covenants, Remonſtrances,</hi> invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably
to defend and maintain them, ſhall ſtill ſo <hi>underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue</hi>
them now at laſt, (as <hi>moſt</hi> actually have done) as <hi>not to
eſteem them worth the owning, maintaining, vindicating,</hi> or
<hi>perpetuating</hi> any longer; and thereby draw upon their
heads the <hi>real guilt</hi> of all thoſe <hi>bloody Wars, Murders, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults,
Violencies, Rapines, Oppreſſions, Sins, Miſchiefs, Illegal
Taxes, Exciſes, Exorb tancies,</hi> which their many late yeers
pretended <hi>Neceſſary Defence</hi> and <hi>Preſervation</hi> have brought
upon our three whole Nations; let them henceforth, like
ſo many daſtardly <hi>conquered Bondſlaves,</hi> bored thorow the
ears, publikely diſavow, diſclaim, renounce, abjure them,
for themſelves and their Poſterities for ever, as meer
<hi>worthleſs toys,</hi> or <hi>pernicious inventions,</hi> fit onely to kindle
perpetual Wars and Diſcords between King and People,
Head and Members, Superiours and Inferiours; or, as poor
<hi>ſlender Cobwebs,</hi> (as now they prove) fit to hold none
within compaſs but the very <hi>weakeſt flyes;</hi> broken thorow
with <hi>eaſe</hi> and <hi>impunity</hi> by every <hi>greater fly,</hi> creeping up into
any <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Supreme Authority,</hi> by <hi>Right</hi> or <hi>Wrong;</hi> and
<hi>ſwept down to the very ground,</hi> by every <hi>New Broom</hi> in the
hand of <hi>upſtart Innovators.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if, upon ſaddeſt deliberation, they ſhall really eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate
them to be ſuch <hi>incomparable, rich, precious jewels,</hi> and
<hi>ancient inheritances,</hi> as are every way worth the infinite
Treaſures, Wars, Blood, Cares, Conſultations, Troubles,
heretofore and of late yeers expended, both to gain, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,
confirm, and perpetuate them, to them and their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities
for ever, as their principal <hi>earthly Security</hi> and
<hi>Pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itude;</hi> I hope they will all then unanimouſly hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth
conclude with the <hi>Poe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non minor eſt virtus quàm quaerere, PARTA TUERI:</hi>
and both by their <hi>Votes,</hi> and <hi>Actions,</hi> return the ſelf-ſame
peremptory magnanimous anſwer to any <hi>Caeſar, Conqueror,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118951:5"/>
Potentate, Power,</hi> or <hi>Combination</hi> of men whatſoever, (who
ſhall endeavour by force, fraud, or flattery, to compel or
perſwade them, to ſell, reſigne, betray, or give up theſe
their <hi>Anceſtral</hi> Priviledges, Inheritances, Birth-rights, to
them) as <hi>Naboth</hi> once did to King <hi>Ahab, 1 King.</hi> 21. 3.
<hi>The Lord forbid it us, that we ſhould give</hi> (ſell, or betray) <hi>the
INHERITANCE OF OUR FATHERS</hi> (and our Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities
likewiſe) <hi>unto thee,</hi> or you; though they ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
for this Anſwer and refuſal, as much as <hi>Naboth</hi> did from
<hi>bloody Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezebel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whatever <hi>lowe price</hi> or <hi>estim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te</hi> this <hi>ſpurious, ſtupid,
ſordid, ſlaviſh Age</hi> may ſet upon theſe <hi>richeſt Pearls;</hi> yet
for my own particular, upon ſerious conſideration of theſe
<hi>Chronological Collections,</hi> and the Solemn Oathes, Prote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
Vows, <hi>League and Covenant,</hi> obliging me to defend
them to the uttermoſt; I value the whole <hi>Nations publike,</hi>
and <hi>my own</hi> (with my <hi>cordial friends) private intereſt</hi> in
them, at ſo <hi>high a rate,</hi> that I would rather <hi>chearfully part
with ten thouſand lives, and all the treaſures of the Nation,</hi>
were I owner of them, then wittingly, negligently, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily
ſell, betray, or reſigne them up to any Mortals
or <hi>Powers</hi> whatſoever, upon any Pretences or Conditions,
after all my former Publications, Conteſts, Sufferings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
for their <hi>juſt</hi> Defence.</p>
            <p>Now to the end all others might now take ſpecial no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
of the ineſtimable value our Anceſtors in all Ages
have ſet upon them, and what ſucceſſive Wars, Conflicts,
they have chearfully undertaken for their preſervation; I
have, at <hi>vacant hours</hi> compiled this enſuing <hi>Vindication and
Collection</hi> of the <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Fund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mental Liberties, Franchiſes, Laws</hi>
of all <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gliſh Free-men,</hi> which I ſhall bequeath to my <hi>moſt
beloved native Country</hi> in general, and every real <hi>Heroick
Patron</hi> of them in particular, as the <hi>beſt Legacie</hi> I can leave
behinde me, both for their <hi>preſent</hi> and <hi>future Enfranchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
Immunity, Security</hi> from all <hi>Arbitrary tyranny, Slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi>
and <hi>yokes of Bondage,</hi> under which they have a long
time <hi>langu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhed,</hi> and <hi>lamented,</hi> in the <hi>bitterneſs of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118951:6"/>
The Method I reſolve herein to purſue, is this:</p>
            <p>1. <hi>I ſhall produce ſome punctual</hi> Authorities <hi>of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
to evidence,</hi> That the Kingdom and Free-men of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
have ſome ancient Hereditary juſt Rights, Liberties, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges,
Franchiſes, Laws and Customs, properly called FUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAMENTAL;
and likewiſe a FUNDAMENTAL Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
no ways to be altered, undermined, ſubverted, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly
or indirectly, to the Publike prejudice, under pain of high-Treaſon
in thoſe who ſhall attempt it, eſpecially by fraud, force,
or armed power.</p>
            <p>2. I ſhall in brief <hi>Propoſitions</hi> preſent you with the
chiefeſt and moſt conſiderable of them, which our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors
in former ages, and our lateſt real Parliaments have
reſolved to be, and eagerly contended for, as FUNDA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTAL,
eſſential to their being and well-being, as a
Free People, Kingdom, Reipublike, unwilling to be <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved</hi>
under any Yokes of Tyranny, any Arbitrary <hi>Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>
or <hi>Powers</hi> whatſoever. And then give you a brief
Touch of their ſeveral late <hi>unparallel'd violations,</hi> both by
the <hi>Edicts</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> of <hi>uſurping Powers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. I ſhall in a <hi>Chronological</hi> way tender you a large <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical
Catalogue</hi> of Conteſts, Votes, Declarations, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances,
Oathes, Vows, Proteſtations, Covenants, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements,
Evidences, Statutes, Charters, Writs, Records,
Judgements, and Authorities, in all ages, undeniably evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencing,
declaring, vindicating, eſtabliſhing, perpetuating
theſe <hi>Fundamental Hereditary Rights, Liberties, Priviledges,
Franchiſes, Cuſtoms, Laws,</hi> and abundantly manifeſting the
extraordinary <hi>care, induſtry, zeal, courage, wiſdom, vigilancy</hi>
of our <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> to defend, preſerve, and perpetuate them
to poſterity, without the leaſt <hi>violation</hi> or <hi>diminution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. I ſhall vindicate the <hi>excellencie, indifferencie,</hi> and <hi>lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi>
of <hi>trying</hi> all Malefactors whatſoever by <hi>Juries of their
peers,</hi> upon <hi>legal Proceſs</hi> and <hi>Indictments;</hi> and manifeſt the
<hi>illegality, injuſtice, partiality, dangerous conſequences,</hi> of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting
or introducing <hi>any other</hi> form of <hi>Trials,</hi> by <hi>New,
Arbitrary, Martial Commiſſions,</hi> or <hi>Courts of High Juſtice,</hi> (or
rather<note n="*" place="margin">Summum jus, eſt ſumma inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c. de Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s, p.</hi> 611.</note> 
               <hi>Injuſtice</hi>) inconſiſtent with, and deſtructive to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118951:6"/>
               <hi>Fundamental Rights, Liberties, Priviledges, Laws, Franchiſes</hi>
of the <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> and of moſt dangerous Preſident to
Poſterity; being ſet up by the greateſt <hi>Pretenders</hi> to Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
Liberty, Law, and the chiefeſt inveighers againſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary
Regal Tyranny and Power, which never publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
eſtabliſhed them by any Law, and may fall to imitate
them in future Ages.</p>
            <p>Each of theſe I intend to proſecute in diſtinct Chapters
in their order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the firſt of theſe:</hi> That the Kingdom and Free-men of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>England,</hi> have ſome Ancient Hereditary Rights, Liberties, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges,
Franchiſes, Laws and Cuſtoms, properly called FUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAMENTAL;
and likewiſe a FUNDAMENTAL <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERNMENT,
no ways to be altered, undermined, ſubverted,
directly or indirectly, under pain of High-treaſon in thoſe who
ſhall attempt it, eſpecially by fraud, force, or armed power.</p>
            <p>I ſhall confirm the firſt part of it, by theſe enſuing pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual
Authorities of moment, againſt thoſe<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lilb.</hi> tryed and cast, <hi>p. 39, 40, 142. to</hi> 148 and elſewhere. <hi>John Canne</hi>'s 2 Voice from the Temple. <hi>John Rogers</hi> Mene, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, Per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z, <hi>p. 6. Lilly</hi> and <hi>Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peper</hi> in their prognoſtications <hi>Anno 1653. &amp; 1654. See the</hi> Armies Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals.</note> 
               <hi>traytorous</hi>
late-publiſhed Pamphlets, which profeſſedly deny it, and
endeavour a <hi>total abrogation</hi> of all <hi>former Laws,</hi> to ſet up <hi>a
New Model</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> to rule us for the future,
according to their Pleaſures.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, the expreſs words of the <hi>Great Charters</hi> of
the <hi>Liberties of England,</hi> granted by<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Matth. Paris, p. 216 &amp; Magna Chart. 9, 11. 3 <hi>H.</hi> 3. c. 1. &amp; 38. 25 <hi>E.</hi> 1. c. 1, &amp;c. 28 <hi>E.</hi> 1. c. 1, &amp;c. Cook'<hi>s 2 Inſtit.</hi> p. 2, 77.</note> King <hi>John,</hi> Anno
1215. in the 17 yeer of his Reign; regranted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
by King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, in the ninth yeer of his
Reign, and ſundry times afterwards; and by King <hi>Edward</hi>
the firſt, in the 25 and 28 yeers of his Reign: wherein
theſe three Kings ſucceſſively, by their ſeveral <hi>Grand Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi>
under their <hi>Great Seals,</hi> did <hi>grant, give,</hi> and <hi>confirm,</hi> to
<hi>all the Free-men of the Realm of England,</hi> FOR THEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SELVES
AND THEIR HEIRS FOR EVER, the <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoms,
Liberties</hi> therein contained; TO HAVE AND TO
HOLD THEM, TO THEM AND THEIR HEIRS,
FROM THEM AND THEIR HEIRS FOR EVER. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding
their Charters thus: <hi>All theſe Customs and Liberties
aforeſaid, which we have granted to be holden within this our
Realm, as much as appertaineth</hi> TO US AND OUR
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118951:7"/>
HEIRS, WE SHALL OBSERVE. <hi>And</hi> ALL MEN OF
THIS OUR REALM, AS WELL SPIRITUAL AS
TEMPORAL, (<hi>as much as in them is) ſhall obſerve the ſame
againſt all perſons in likewiſe. And we have granted unto
them,</hi> THAT NEITHER WE NOR OUR HEIRS
SHALL PROCURE OR DO ANY THING WHERE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BY
THE LIBERTIES IN THESE CHARTERS CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAINED,
SHALL BE INFRINGED OR BROKEN.
<hi>We ratifying and approving theſe Gifts and Grants aforeſaid,</hi>
CONFIRM <hi>and</hi> CORROBORATE ALL THE SAME,
FOR US AND OUR HEIRS PERPETUALLY: <hi>and
by theſe Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſents</hi> (as the later Charters run) <hi>do renew the
ſame: Willing and granting,</hi> FOR US AND OUR HEIRS,
THAT THESE CHARTERS, AND ALL AND SIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GULAR
THEIR ARTICLES, FOR EVER SHALL
BE STEDFASTLY, FIRMLY, AND INVIOLABLY
OBSERVED.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Edward Cook,</hi> (that reverend learned Judge and
Profeſſor of our Laws) in his Preface to his <hi>ſecond Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,</hi>
and p. 2. and 77. thereof, wherein he comments on
this <hi>Great Charter,</hi> (printed by two Orders of the Houſe of
Commons in Parliament, dated 12 <hi>Maii</hi> 1641. and 30
<hi>Junit</hi> 1642.) reſolves in direct terms, <hi>That the Great Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
was for the moſt part declaratory of the Principal Grounds of
THE FUNDAMENTAL LAWS OF</hi> ENGLAND:
<hi>That theſe words therein, [for us and our heirs for ever] were
added, to avoid all ſcruples;</hi> THAT THIS GREAT PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAMENTARY:
CHARTER MIGHT LIVE AND
TAKE EFFECT IN ALL SUCCESSIONS OF AGES
FOR EVER. A clear Reſolution, that the principal Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,
Cuſtoms, Laws, contained in theſe <hi>Great Charters,</hi>
and ratified by them, are both <hi>Fundamental, perpetual,</hi> and
<hi>unalterable;</hi> being ſince <hi>confirmed in all points by neer fourty
ſeveral ſpecial Acts of Parliament</hi> in ſucceeding Parliaments:
and likewiſe by the <hi>Solemn Oathes of our Kings, Nobles,
Judges, Great Officers,</hi> and of the <hi>People</hi> too, (all ſeveral
times <hi>ſworn to defend and maintain the ſame</hi>) and by ſundry
<hi>Solemn Excommunications againſt the infringers or contemners
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118951:7"/>
of them in any kinde;</hi> as I ſhall prove more fully in the third
Chapter.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, the punctual Reſolution of the whole <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
Parliament of 1 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> even in a Printed Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
chap. 2. and of King <hi>James</hi> himſelf, in his Speech
therein, as is evident by this <hi>Prologue</hi> to that Act: <hi>Whereas
his moſt excellent Majeſtie hath been pleaſed, out of his great
wiſdom and judgement, not onely to repreſent unto us, by his own
prudent and Princely Speech on the firſt day of this Parliament,
how much he deſired (in regard of his inward and gracious af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
to both the famous and ancient Realms of</hi> England <hi>and</hi>
Scotland, <hi>now united in Allegiance, and by all ſubjection IN
HIS ROYAL PERSON, TO HIS MAJESTY AND HIS
POSTERITY FOR EVER) that by a ſpeedy, mature, and ſound
Deliberation, ſuch a future Union might follow, as ſhould make
perfect that mutual love, and uniformity of Maners and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms,
which Almighty God in his providence, for the ſtrength
and ſafety of both Realms, hath ſo far already begun, in apparent
ſight of all the world; but alſo hath vouchſafed to expreſs many
ways, how far it is, and EVER SHALL BE, from his Royal
and ſincere care and affection to the Subjects of</hi> England, TO
ALTER OR INNOVATE THE FUNDAMENTAL
AND ANCIENT LAWS, PRIVILEDGES, &amp; GOOD
CUSTOMS OF THIS KINGDOM; <hi>whereby not onely</hi>
HIS ROYAL AUTHORITY, <hi>but</hi> THE PEOPLES SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CURITY
OF LANDS, LIVINGS, <hi>and</hi> PRIVILEDGES
(<hi>both in General and Particular</hi>) ARE PRESERVED AND
MAINTAINED;<note place="margin">Nota.</note> 
               <hi>and,</hi> BY THE ABOLISHING OR
ALTERATION OF THE WHICH, IT IS IMPOS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIBLE
BUT THAT PRESENT CONFUSION WILL
FALL UPON THE WHOLE STATE AND FRAME
OF THIS KINGDOM, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In which memorable
Clauſe, theſe four things are obſervable 1. That the
Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dom and People of <hi>England</hi> have Fundamental anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
good Laws, Priviledges, and Cuſtoms. 2. That theſe
are no ways to be altered or innovated; and that it always
hath been, is, and ever ſhall be, far from the thoughts and
intents of all good Kings, Governours, and Parliaments,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118951:8"/>
who bear a ſincere care and affection to the Subjects of
<hi>England,</hi> to alter or innovate them. 3. That by theſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
good Laws, Priviledges, and Cuſtoms, not onely the
Kings Regal authority, but the Peoples Security of Lands,
Livings, and Priviledges, (both in general and particular)
are preſerved and maintained. 4. That by the aboliſhing
or altering of them, <hi>it is impoſſible,</hi> but that preſent confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
will fall upon the whole State and frame of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.
Which I wiſh all <hi>Innovators</hi> and <hi>New Modellers</hi> of
<hi>our Laws,</hi> would now at laſt ſay ſeriouſly to heart, and the
whole Kingdom and <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> ſadly conſider, who
have found it an <hi>Experimental truth</hi> of late yeers, and no
imaginary feigned <hi>Speculation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third is, The <hi>Remonſtrance of the whole Houſe of
Commons</hi> in Parliament, delivered in writing to K. <hi>James,</hi>
in the Parliament of 7 <hi>Jac. anno</hi> 1610. which begins thus.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="remonstrance">
            <head>To the Kings most Excellent Majeſty.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt gracious Soveraign,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHereas we your Majeſties moſt humble Subjects, the
<hi>Commons aſſembled in Parliament,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Prop. 1. &amp; 6. in <hi>chap.</hi> 2.</note> have received,
firſt by Meſſage, and ſince by Speech, from your Majeſtie, a
Command of reſtraint, <hi>from debating in Parliament your
Majeſties Right of impoſing upon your ſubjects goods ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
out of, or imported into this Realm,</hi> yet allowing us
to examine the grievance of theſe Impoſitions, in regard of
quantity, time, and other circumſtances of diſproportion thereto
incident: We your ſaid humble Subjects nothing doubting but
that your Majeſtie had no intent by that command, to infringe
<hi>THE ANCIENT AND FUNDAMENTAL RIGHTS
OF THE LIBERTY OF PARLIAMENT,</hi> in point of
exact diſcuſſing of all matters concerning them and their Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
Goods, and Rights whatſoever; which yet we cannot but
conceive to be done in effect by this command, Do with all hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
duty <hi>make</hi> this Remonſtrance to your Majestie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First, We hold it an AN ANCIENT, GENERAL, and
UNDOUBTED RIGHT OF PARLIAMENT, to</hi> debate
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118951:8"/>
freely all matters which do properly concern the Suject,
and his Right or Eſtate: which freedom of debate being
once fore-cloſed,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> THE ESSENCE OF THE LIBERTY
OF PARLIAMENT IS WITHAL DISSOLVED.</p>
            <p>Here the whole Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> in a <hi>ſpecial Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance</hi>
to King <hi>James,</hi> (printed and publiſhed by <hi>Order of
a Committee of the Houſe of Commons for licenſing of book<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
dated 20 <hi>Maii, 1641. 17 Caroli</hi>) declare, reſolve, vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate,
and maintain, One principal, ancient, Fundamental,
general, undoubted Right of the Liberty of Parliament,
againſt the Kings intrenchment on it: <hi>Of which ſhould they
be but once fore-cloſed, the Eſſence of the Liberty of Parliament
is withal diſſolved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And peradventure it may not be unworthy the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
Diſquiſition of the next enſuing nominal or real <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi>
to examine, whether ſome <hi>Clauſes</hi> and <hi>Reſtrictions</hi>
in the 9, 12, 14, 16, 17, 21, 22, 24, 25, 27, 30, 32, 33, 36,
37, 38, 39, 40 <hi>Articles</hi> (or Strings) of the New <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
intituled, <hi>The Government of the Commonwealth of</hi>
England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and the Dominions thereunto
belonging;</hi> as it <hi>was publikely declared at Weſtminſter the</hi> 16
<hi>day of</hi> December, 1653. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do not as much, nay far
<hi>more intrench upon the ancient, Fundamental, General, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted
Right and Liberty of Parliament,</hi> and Parliamentary
free Debates, to the diſſolution of the <hi>Eſſential Liberty of
all future Parliaments,</hi> as this Command of King <hi>James</hi>
did, or as the Biſhops late <hi>Canons</hi> impoſed on the Clergie
in and by the <hi>Convocation, Anno</hi> 1640. ever did; and
this Clauſe in their <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Oath then made, (now imitated
by others, who condemned it:) <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do ſwear, that I
will never give my conſent</hi> TO ALTER THE GOVERN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT
OF THIS CHURCH BY ARCH-BISHOPS,
BISHOPS, DEANS, AND ARCH-DEACONS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> AS
IT STANDS NOW ESTABLISHED, AND AS BY
RIGHT IT OUGHT TO STAND:<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Cant.</hi> Doom, <hi>p.</hi> 19, 26. 40. Diurn. Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences, <hi>p.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Reſolved by the
whole houſe of Commons,</hi> and <hi>Peers</hi> too, without one diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting
voice, <hi>in Parliament,</hi> Decemb. 1640. to be <hi>a most
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118951:9"/>
dangerous and illegal Oath, contrary to THE RIGHTS and
PRIVILEDGES OF</hi> PARLIAMENT, <hi>and to the FUNDA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTAL
LAWS &amp; STATUTES OF THE REALM,</hi>
&amp;c. <hi>and OF DANGEROUS CONSEQUENCE.</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving
whereof was objected to the late Arch-biſhop of
<hi>Canterbury,</hi> in his <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>Additional Articles of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment,</hi>
to be <hi>HIGH TREASON;</hi> for which, amongſt
other things, he <hi>lost his head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth is, the notable <hi>Petition of Grievance</hi> of the
<hi>whole Houſe of Commons in Parliament,</hi> preſented to King
<hi>James</hi> in the ſeventh yeer of his Reign, after their Vote
againſt his right to lay any <hi>Impoſitions</hi> on Goods imported
or exported, without aſſent of Parliament; in theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing
words.</p>
            <p>THe Policie and Conſtitution of this your Majeſties King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,<note place="margin">See Propoſ. 1. in chap. 2.</note>
appropriates unto the Kings of this Realm, with aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
of Parliament, as well the Soveraign power of making
Laws, as that of taxing or impoſing upon the Subjects Goods or
Merchandizes, wherein they have juſtly ſuch a Property, as
may not without their conſent be altered or changed: this is
the cauſe, that the People of this Kingdom, as they have<note n="*" place="margin">O how are they now degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted!</note> ever
ſhewed themſelves faithful and loving to their Kings, and ready
to aid them in all their juſt occaſions,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> with voluntary Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:
<hi>SO HAVE THEY BEEN</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">And ſhould they not be ſo now, then?</note> 
               <hi>EVER CAREFUL
TO PRESERVE THEIR OWN LIBERTIES AND
RIGHTS, WHEN ANY THING HATH BEEN
DONE TO PREJUDICE OR IMPEACH THE SAME.</hi>
And therefore when their Princes, either occaſioned by War, or by
their own bounty, or by any other Neceſſity, have without conſent
of Parliament ſet on Impoſitions, either within the Land, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r upon
Commodities exported or imported by the Merchants, they have
in open Parliament complained of it, in that it was done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
their conſents; AND THEREUPON<note n="*" place="margin">And ſhall we now at last fail h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rein?</note> NEVER FAI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LED
TO OBTAIN A SPEEDY AND FULL RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DRESS,
without any<note n="†" place="margin">Howdare then any ſelf created powers, who are neither Kings nor Parliam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s now arrogate to themſelves, or exerciſe ſuch a ſuper-Regal ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary power &amp; prerogative?</note> Claim made by the Kings, of any
Power or Prerogative in that point. And though <hi>THE
LAW OF PROPERTY BE ORIGINAL,</hi> and carefully
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118951:9"/>
preſerved by the Common Lawes of this Realm, <hi>WHICH
ARE AS ANCIENT AS THE KINGDOM IT SELF;</hi>
yet thoſe famous Kings, for the better contentment and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
of their loving Subjects, agreed, <hi>THAT THIS OLD
FUNDAMENTAL RIGHT (obſerve the words</hi>) ſhould
be further declared, <hi>AND ESTABLISHED BY ACT
OF PARLIAMENT,</hi> wherein it is provided, That no ſuch
Charge ſhould ever be laid upon the People without their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
conſents, as may appear by ſundry Records of former
times.</p>
            <p>We therefore your Majeſties moſt humble Commons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
in Parliament,<note place="margin">Nota.</note>
               <note n="*" place="margin">And O that we would ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain!</note> FOLLOWING THE EXAMPLE
OF THIS WORTHY CARE OF OUR ANCESTORS,
AND OUT OF OUR DUTY TO THOSE FOR WHOM
WE SERVE, finding that your Majeſty, without advice of
your Lords and Commons, hath lately (in times of Peace)
SET BOTH GREATER IMPOSITIONS, AND FAR
MORE IN NUMBER THEN ANY YOUR NOBLE
ANCESTORS DID EVER IN TIME OF WAR, do
with all humility preſent this moſt juſt and neceſſary Petition
unto your Majesty, THAT ALL IMPOSITIONS SET
WITHOUT ASSENT IN PARLIAMENT, MAY BE
QUITE ABOLISHED AND TAKEN AWAY. And
that your Majeſty likewiſe in imitation of your Royal PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GENITORS,
will be pleaſed, that a Law in your time, and
during this Seſſion of Parliament, may be alſo made, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare,
<hi>THAT ALL IMPOSITIONS OF ANY KIND
SET, OR TO BE SET UPON YOUR PEOPLE, THEIR
GOODS OR MERCHANDIZES, SAVE ONLY BY
COMMON CONSENT IN PARLIAMENT, ARE
AND SHALL BE VOID;</hi> wherein your Majesty ſhall
not only <hi>GIVE YOUR SUBJECTS GREAT SATIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FACTION
IN POINT OF THEIR RIGHT;</hi> but
alſo bring exceeding joy and comfort to them who now ſuffer,
partly through the abating of the price of Native Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
and partly through the raiſing of all Forraign, to the
overt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> row of Merchants, and Shipping, the cauſing of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
dearth, and decay of all wealth among your people, who
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118951:10"/>
will be thereby no leſs diſcouraged, then diſabled to ſupply your
Majesty when occaſion ſhall require.</p>
            <p>In which <hi>memorable Petition,</hi> the whole <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi>
reſolve in direct terms: 1. <hi>That the Subjects of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
<hi>have old original Fundamental Rights,</hi> (and more
particularly <hi>in the Property of their goods, exempted from all
Impoſitions whatſoever in times of Peace or War, without
their common conſent in Parliament) declared and establiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
both by the ancient Common Law of</hi> England, <hi>and ſundry
Acts of Parliament, and Records of former times.</hi> 2. They
declare, the conſtant vigilant care, zeal of our Anceſtors
and former Parliaments in all Ages, inviolably to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,
defend, preſerve the ſame againſt all encroachments,
together with their own care, duty and vigilancy in this
kind in that very Parliament. 3. They relate the readineſs
of our Kings to ratifie theſe their <hi>Fundamental Rights</hi> by
new <hi>Acts of Parliament,</hi> when they have been violated
in any kinde. 4. They declare the benefit accruing both
to <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> by the inviolable preſervation and
eſtabliſhment of this <hi>old Fundamental Right,</hi> and the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs
accruing to both by the infringement thereof, by
<hi>arbitrary illegal Impoſitions, without full conſent in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
5. They earneſtly (in point of conſcience, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
and duty to thoſe for whom they ſerved) Petition
his Majeſty, for a <hi>new Law and Declaration againſt all new
Impoſitions and Taxes on Inland Goods, or Merchandizes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
or exported without the Peoples free conſent in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
as null, void, utterly to be aboliſhed and taken away.</hi>
Whether it will not be abſolutely neceſſary for the whole
<hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> and the next enſuing Notional, or real
<hi>Parliament</hi> to Proſecute, Enact, Eſtabliſh ſuch a Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and Law againſt all ſuch future <hi>arbitrary, illegal, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive
Taxes, Impoſitions, Exciſes,</hi> that have been impoſed
and continued for many years together on the whole
Kingdom, by new extravagant, <hi>ſelf-created,</hi> uſurping Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my-<hi>Officers,
and other Powers,</hi> without free and full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
of the People in <hi>lawful Engliſh Parliaments,</hi> againſt
all former Laws, Declarations, and Reſolutions in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118951:10"/>
to their great <hi>oppreſſion,</hi> enſlaving, undoing, and
that in <hi>far greater proportions, multiplicity, and variety,</hi> then
ever in former Ages, <hi>without</hi> the leaſt intermiſſion; and
likewiſe againſt their late <hi>declared deſign, to perpetuate
them on our exhauſted Nation, without alteration or diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
(beyond and againſt all Preſidents of former Ages)
both in times of <hi>Peace and War for the future,</hi> by the 27,
28, 39, 30, 9. <hi>Articles</hi> of the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> entituled, <hi>The
Government of the Commonwealth of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I remit
to their moſt ſerious con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>derations to determine, if ever
they reſolve to be <hi>Engliſh Freemen</hi> again, or to imitate
the <hi>wiſdom, prudence, zeal, courage, and laudable examples
of their worthy Ancestors,</hi> from which they cannot now
degenerate without the greateſt <hi>Infamy,</hi> and enſlaving of
themſelves with their Poſterities for ever, to the <hi>arbitrary
wills of preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt or future Uſurpers</hi> on their <hi>Fundamental
Rights and Libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ties,</hi> in an higher degree then ever in any
precedent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ges, under the <hi>Greateſt Conquerors</hi> or <hi>Kings,</hi>
after all their late, coſtly, bloudy <hi>Wars</hi> for their <hi>Defence</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the <hi>Behe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ded King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fifth is,</hi> A learned and neceſſary Argument made in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
the Commons Houſe of Parliament, <hi>Anno 7. Jacobi,</hi> to
prove, That each Subject hath a Propriety in his Goods; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
alſo, the extent of the Kings Prerogative in Impoſitions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the Goods of Merchants exported or imported, &amp;c. <hi>By a
late</hi> learned Judg of this Kingdom, <hi>printed at</hi> London <hi>by</hi>
Richard Biſhop, 1641. <hi>and</hi> Ordered <hi>to be pub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſhed in Print,</hi>
at a Committee appointed by the Honourable Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,
for examination and Licenſing of B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oks. 20. <hi>Maii,</hi>
1641. <hi>In which Parliamentary Argument,</hi> p. 8, 11, 16.
<hi>I finde theſe direct Paſſages:</hi> That the New Im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſitions
contained in the Boo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Rates, impoſed on Merchandizes,
imported and exported by the K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs Prerogative, and Letters
Patents, without conſent in Parliament, is againſt <hi>THE NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TURAL
FRAME AND CONSTITUTION OF THE
POLICY OF THIS KINGDOME,</hi> which is Jus Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum
Regn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>AND SO SUBVERTETH THE FUNDA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTAL
LAW OF THE REALM,</hi> and introduceth a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118951:11"/>
new form of State and Government: Can any man give me a
reaſon, why the King can only in Parliament make Lawes?
No man ever read any Law, whereby it was ſo ordained; and
yet no man ever read, that any King practiſed the contrary;
therefore <hi>IT IS THE ORIGINAL RIGHT OF THE
KINGDOM,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nota.</note> 
               <hi>AND THE VERY NATURAL CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STITUTION
OF OUR STATE AND POLICY,</hi>
being one of the higheſt Rights of Soveraign Power. If the
King alone out of Parliament may impoſe,<note n="*" place="margin">And do not thoſe do ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lay mont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Customs, and N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w-Impoſt on us daily out of Parliament, and that for many moneths and years yet to come, againſt the Letter of their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument and Oath too?</note> 
               <hi>HE ALTER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ETH
THE LAW</hi> OF <hi>ENGLAND</hi> IN <hi>ONE OF
THESE TWO MAIN FUNDAMENTAL POINTS;</hi>
He muſt either take the Subjects Goods from them, without
aſſent of the Party, which is againſt the Law, or elſe he muſt
give his own Letters Patents the force of a Law, to alter the
property of the Subjects Goods, which is alſo againſt the Law.</p>
            <p>In this and ſundry other <hi>Arguments,</hi> (touching the
<hi>Right of Impoſitions</hi>) in the Commons Houſe of Parliament
by the Members of it, arguing againſt them, it was fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
averred, and at laſt voted and reſolved by the
Houſe, 7. <hi>Jacobi. That ſuch Impoſitions without conſent in
Parliament, were</hi> AGAINST THE ORIGINAL FUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAMENTAL
LAWS AND PROPERTY OF THE
SUBJECT, <hi>and Original Right, Frame, and Conſtitution of
the Kingdom;</hi> as the <hi>Notes</hi> and <hi>Journals</hi> of that Parliament
evidence: An expreſs Parliamentary reſolution in point,
for what I here aſſert.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſixth is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">6.</note> A Conference deſired by the Lords, and had
by a Committee of both Houſes, concerning the Rights and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges
of the Subject, 3. Aprilis. 4. Caroli, 1628. <hi>entred
in the</hi> Parliament Journal of 4. Caroli, <hi>and ſince printed
at</hi> London, 1642. <hi>In the</hi> Introduction <hi>to which</hi> Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<hi>Sir</hi> Dudley Diggs, <hi>by the</hi> Commons Houſe Order,
<hi>uſed theſe expreſſions:</hi> My good Lords, whileſt we the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,
out of our good affections, were ſeeking for money,
we found, I cannot ſay a Book of the Law, but many <hi>A
FUNDAMENTAL POINT THEREOF NEGLECT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ED
AND BROKEN,</hi> which hath occaſioned our deſire
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118951:11"/>
of this Conference: Wherein I am firſt commanded to ſhew un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
your Lordſhips in general, That the Laws of <hi>England</hi> are
grounded on Reaſon more antient then Books, conſiſting much
in unwritten Cuſtoms, yet ſo full of Juſtice and true Equity,
that your moſt Honorable Predeceſſors and Anceſtors propug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
them with a <hi>NOLUMUS MUTARI;</hi> and ſo ancient,
that from the <hi>Saxons</hi> daies, notwithſtanding the injuries and
ruines of time, they have continued in moſt parts the ſame, &amp;c.
Be pleaſed then to know, <hi>THAT IT IS AN UNDOUBT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ED
AND FUNDAMENTAL POINT OF THIS SO
ANCIENT COMMON LAW OF</hi> ENGLAND, <hi>THAT
THE SUBJECT HATH A TRUE PROPERTY IN
HIS GOODS AND POSSESSIONS,</hi> which doth preſerve
as ſacred that <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> that is the Nurſe of Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,
and the Mother of Courage, and without which there
can be no Juſtice, of which <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> is the proper ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.
Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>UNDOUBTED RIGHT OF FREE SUB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JECTS,</hi>
hath lately not a little been invaded and prejudiced
by Preſſures, the more grievous, becauſe they have been pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued
by impriſonment, contrary to the Franchiſes of this Land,
&amp;c. <hi>which the</hi> Commons Houſe <hi>proved by many</hi> Statutes
<hi>and</hi> Records in all Ages, <hi>in that Conference, to the full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
of the Lords Houſe; ſince publiſhed in print.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſeventh is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">7.</note> 
               <hi>The Vote of the</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">See <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburies</hi> Doom, p. 19. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urnal Occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, p. 13.</note> whole Houſe of
Commons, 16. December, 1640. Nullo contradicente, <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
in their</hi> Journal, <hi>and printed in</hi> Diurnal Occurrences,
p. 13. That the Canons made <hi>in the</hi> Convocation (<hi>Anno</hi>
1640.) <hi>ARE AGAINST THE FUNDAMENTAL
LAWS OF THE REALM,</hi> the Property and Liberty of
the Subject, the Right of Parliament, and contained divers
things tending to Faction and Sedition.</p>
            <p>The eighth Authority is,<note place="margin">8.</note>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Exact Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, &amp;c. p. 112, 113.</note> The Votes of both
Houſes of Parliament, <hi>concerning the ſecurity of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
of</hi> England, <hi>and Dominion of</hi> Wales, 15. <hi>Martii</hi> 1641.
<hi>Ordered by the Lords and Commons in Parliament to be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
printed and publiſhed</hi> (as they were then by themſelves,
and afterwards with other Votes and Orders) <hi>Reſolved
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118951:12"/>
upon the Queſtion,</hi> nemine contradicente; <hi>That in caſe of</hi>
extream danger, and of his Majeſties refuſal, the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
agreed on by both Houſes for the <hi>Militia,</hi> doth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige
the people,<note place="margin">See Chap. 2. Propoſition 3, 7</note> and ought to be obeyed, by THE FUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAMENTAL
LAWS OF THIS KINGDOM. A very
vain, falſe, abſurd, and deluſory Vote, if there be no ſuch
Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as ſome now affirm.</p>
            <p>The ninth punctual Authority is,<note place="margin">9.</note>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Exact Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, p. 850, 854, 887, 888.</note> 
               <hi>A ſecond Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
of the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament,
concerning the Commiſſion of Array;</hi> printed by their ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<hi>Order</hi> of 12. <hi>Januarii</hi> 1642. Wherein are theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveable
paſſages. The <hi>main drift of the anſwer is to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi>
That the King by the Common Law may grant ſuch
a Commiſſion of Array as this is, upon this ground, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
it's for the defence of the Kingdom:</hi> And, that the
power which he hath to grant it by the <hi>Common Law,</hi> is
not taken away by the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> or any <hi>former Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute,</hi>
but the King notwithſtanding any of them, <hi>may
charge the Subjects for Defence of the Kingdom, ſo as the
charge impoſed come not to himſelf, nor to his particular ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe grounds thus laid, extend not to the Commiſſion of
Array alone, but to all other charges that his Majeſty ſhall
impoſe upon his Subjects, upon pretence of Defence of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;
for there is the ſame reaſon of Law for any other charge
that is pretended for Defence, as for this. If his Majeſty by
the Common Law may charge his Subjects to finde Arms, and
other things in the Commiſſion injoyned, becauſe they are for
Defence of the Kingdom; by the ſame reaſon of Law, he may
command his People to build Caſtles, Forts, and Bulworks,
and after to maintain them with Garriſons, Arms, and Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als,
at their own charges: And by the ſame reaſon he may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
his Subjects to finde Ships, and furniſh them with Men,
Ammunition, and Victuals, and to finde Souldiers pay, coat
and conduct-money; provide victuals for Souldiers, and all
other things <hi>NECESSARY FOR AN</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Do not the Army-Officers now enforce them to all this without a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament?</note> 
               <hi>ARMY;</hi> theſe
things being as neceſſary for Defence, as any thing that can be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118951:12"/>
done in execution of this Commiſſion. And for that expoſition
of the Petition of Right, and other Statutes therein noted,
(if it ſhould hold) doth it not overthrow, as well the Petition
it ſelf, as all other Lawes that have been made for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
benefit against Taxes and other Charges, either in this or
any other Parliament?</p>
            <p>Theſe Poſitions thus laid down and maintained, <hi>DO
SHAKE THE FUNDAMENTAL LAWS OF THE
KINGDOM, (THE ANCIENT BIRTH-RIGHT OF
EVERY SUBJECT) both for THE PROPERTY OF
HIS GOODS, AND LIBERTY, OF HIS PERSON:</hi>
Nay, they ſtrike at the root of Parliaments: What need his
<note n="*" place="margin">Theſe Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulations reach to thoſe at <hi>White-Hall</hi> now, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to impoſe Taxes, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, Exciſes, and make b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Laws, which no Kings there ever did in like nature, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Counc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls in any Age.</note> Majeſty call Parliaments to provide for Defence of the Realm,
when himſelf may compel his Subjects to defend it without
Parliaments? If theſe grounds ſhould hold, what need the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
grant Subſidies in Parliament for Defence of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
in time of real danger, if the King for defence at any
times, when he ſhall only conceive or pretend danger, may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
Charges upon his Subjects without their conſent in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Upon that which hath been ſaid in this and our former</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration,
<hi>we doubt not but all indifferent men will be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
that this Commiſſion of Array is full of danger and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience
to the Subjects of</hi> England, AND AGAINST
THE FUNDAMENTAL LAWS OF THE LAND,
both for PROPERTY OF GOODS, AND LIBERTY
OF PERSON, &amp;c. 2. <hi>As it is against</hi> THE FUNDA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTAL
LAWS OF THE REALM, <hi>ſo no Statute
makes it good, &amp;c. And the Lords and Commons do upon
the whole matter here conclude, that they</hi> are very much ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grieved,
that after ſo many Declarations and ſolemn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations
made by his Majeſty to rule by the known Laws
of this Land, <hi>his Majeſty by advice of his ill Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors
ſhould be perſwaded to ſet ſuch a</hi> Commiſſion on foot,
which is ſo clearly contrary TO THE FUNDAMEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAL
LAWS OF THIS LAND, the Right of Property,
and Liberty of the Subject, <hi>contrary to former</hi> Reſolutions
of Parliament, <hi>and to the</hi> Petition of Right.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:118951:13"/>
I am certain the generality of the Nation are now as
<hi>much</hi> and more <hi>aggrieved,</hi> that ſome who were Parties
to this <hi>Declaration,</hi> and others who have made as many
or more <hi>Declarations</hi> and <hi>Proteſtations</hi> as his <hi>Majeſty</hi> ever
did, to <hi>rule by the known Laws of the Land,</hi> ſhould ſince
this, far exceed his Majeſty in the like, or more exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances
in the <hi>Militia,</hi> Exciſes, Taxes, Impoſitions, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments,
arbitrary extravagant proceedings, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital
executions in new-<hi>erected Courts of Injuſtice,</hi> as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ametrically
contrary as the Kings Commiſſions of <hi>Array,</hi>
to the <hi>Fundamental Laws of the Land</hi> (four times together
ſo ſtiled and inſided on, as ſuch, in this one Declaration of
both Houſes) <hi>the Right of Property of the Subject, contrary
to former Reſolutions,</hi> and the <hi>Petition of Right;</hi> yea (which
is moſt abominable) to their own <hi>Declarations, Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances,
Votes, Proteſtations, Vows, Solemn Leagues and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants</hi>
in Parliament, to their own eternal <hi>Infamy,</hi> as
well as the peoples intolerable oppreſſion and <hi>Slavery,</hi>
who thereupon may juſtly conclude and proteſt againſt
them, as both <hi>Houſes did in the cloſe</hi> of that Declaration
againſt the <hi>Array,</hi> viz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Exact Collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, p. 888.</note> 
               <hi>And the</hi> Lords and Commons
do and ſhall adhere to their former Votes and Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
That all thoſe that are Actors in putting of this
Commiſſion of Array in execution, ſhall be eſteemed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers
of the Peace of the Kingdome, and the Properties
and Liberties of the Subject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The tenth evidence is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">10.</note>
               <note n="a" place="margin">A Collection of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Order<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations of Parliament, p. 451, 452, 457, 458.</note> 
               <hi>the</hi> Vote and Letter of both
Houſes of Parliament <hi>ſent to his Majeſty at</hi> Oxford 9.
March 1643. <hi>in anſwer to his</hi> Majeſties <hi>of the third of</hi>
March, <hi>wherein there is this paſſage:</hi> We the Lords and
Commons aſſembled in the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>have
reſolved, with the concurrent advice and conſent of the</hi>
Commiſſioner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Scotland, <hi>to repreſent to your Majeſty in
all hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ity and plainneſs as followeth;</hi> That this preſent
Parliament convened according to the known and FUNDA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTAL
LAWS OF THE KINGDOM (the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
whereof is eſtabliſhed by a <hi>Law</hi> conſented to by your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſty)
is in effect denied to be a Parliament, &amp;c. <hi>And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118951:13"/>
we think our ſelves bound to let your Majeſty know,</hi>
That ſince the<note n="*" place="margin">Yet forcibly diſſolved by the Army, and ſome new in Power, againſt their Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Oaths, Truſts, Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, Coven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, and an Act of Parliament for their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance; who may do well to peruſe this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. See <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. Propoſition 6. 7.</note> continuance of this Parliament is ſetled by a
<hi>Law,</hi> (which, as all other <hi>Laws</hi> of your Kingdom, your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty
is ſworn to maintain, as we are ſworn to our Allegiance
to your Majeſty, theſe Obligations being reciprocal) we muſt
in duty, and accordingly are reſolved, with our lives and
fortunes, to defend and preſerve the juſt Rights and full Power
of this Parliament: <hi>To which the</hi> Earl of Eſſex (<hi>then Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral)
by both</hi> Houſes direction, <hi>in his Letter to the</hi> Earl
of Forth, Jan. 30. 1643. <hi>adds this Corollary,</hi> My Lord,
the maintenance of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges
thereof, is that for which we are all reſolved to ſpend
our bloud, as being THE FOUNDATION WHEREON
ALL OUR LAWS and LIBERTIES ARE BUILT:
<hi>Which both the</hi> Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<hi>in their</hi> Declaration <hi>of</hi> 23. Martii 1643. <hi>touching
their proceedings upon his Majeſties Letter concerning a</hi>
Treaty of Peace; (<hi>wherein this Earls former Letter is
recited) thus ſecond:</hi> The Parliament of <hi>England</hi> is the
only Baſis, the chief Support and Pillar of our <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,</hi>
&amp;c. <hi>And if notwithſtanding all theſe Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
the King ſhall</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">How much more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, if the Army, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Army-Officers ſhall do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, without queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry puniſhm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt again and again, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie it ſtill in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>?</note> 
               <hi>at his pleaſure diſſolve this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
the Kingdom is not only deprived of the preſent,
but made uncapable of enjoying the benefit of any future
Parliament or Laws, any longer then ſhall ſtand with the
will and pleaſure of the King, and conſequently THE
FUNDAMENTALS OF ALL OUR LAWS &amp; GO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERNMENT
ARE SUBVERTED. Let the Parliament-diſſolving</hi>
Officers, Army, <hi>and their</hi> Confederates <hi>ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
ponder this, with all who ſhall hereafter ſit in</hi> Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>conſider it in the</hi> firſt place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The eleventh is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> 
               <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">A Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c. p. 504.</note> Ordinance of both Houſes of
Parliament, 13. Junii 1644. <hi>for the Forces raiſed in the
County of</hi> Salop, <hi>which begins thus:</hi> The Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
aſſembled in Parliament, taking into their ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations,
the great oppreſſions under which the Inhabitants
of the County of <hi>Salop,</hi> by reaſon of inſupportable Taxes,
&amp;c. and the preſent condition of the County, by reaſon of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118951:14"/>
the great number of Iriſh Rebels that have invaded it, and
joyned with Papiſts and other ill-affected Perſons now in thoſe
parts, doth threaten the extirpation of the Proteſtant Religion,
and the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſion of THE FUNDAMENTAL LAWS &amp;
GOVERNMENT OF THE KINGDOM. For prevention
whereof, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The twelfth is</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">A Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c. p. 877, 878, 879.</note> A Declaration of the Commons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
aſſembled in Parliament 17.<note place="margin">12.</note> Aprilis 1646. Of their true
intentions concerning the AN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>IENT &amp; FUNDAMEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAL
GOVERNMENT OF THE KINGDOM, ſecuring
the people againſt <hi>ALL ARBITRARY GOVERNMENT,</hi>
&amp;c. <hi>wherein they complain,</hi> That the Enemy being in deſpair
to accompliſh his deſigns by War, do miſrepreſent our intentions
in the uſe we intended to make of the great Succeſſes God hath
given us, and the happy opportunity to ſettle peace and truth
in the three Kingdoms; to beget a belief that we now deſire to
exceed or ſwerve from our firſt Aims and Principles in the
Undertaking of this War, and to recede from the Solemn League
and Covenant, and Treaties between the two Kingdoms; and
that we would prolong theſe uncomfortable Troubles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Diſtractions, IN<note n="*" place="margin">And is not this now proved a real exper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in ſome of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Remonſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, to their ſhame?</note> ORDER TO ALTER THE FUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAMENTAL
CONSTITUTION &amp; FRAME OF THIS
KINGDOM, to leave all Government in the Church looſe and
unſetled, and our ſelves to exerciſe THE SAME ARBI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRARY
POWER OVER THE PERSONS &amp; ESTATES
OF THE SUBJECTS, which this preſent Parliament hath
thought fit to aboliſh, by taking away the Star-Chamber, High
Commiſſion, and other Arbitrary Courts, and the exorbitant
Power of the Councel Table: (<hi>all which we have ſeen ſince
experimentally verified in every particular in the higheſt
d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gree, notwithſtanding this</hi> Declaration, <hi>by ſome in late
and preſent Power, notwithſtanding this Publication:</hi>)
All which being ſeriouſly conſidered by us, &amp;c. <hi>We do declare,
THAT OUR TRUE &amp; REAL INTENTIONS ARE, &amp;
OUR ENDEAVOR SHALL BE,</hi> to ſettle Religion in the
purity thereof,<note n="*" place="margin">And can moſt of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ns <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> or preſent pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> joy this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> truth or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally? And muſt not they be utterly aſham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, confounded before God and men, when they conſider how they have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, prev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ated with God and men herein in each particular?</note> 
               <hi>TO MAINTAIN THE ANCIENT &amp;FUNDAMENTAL GOVERNMENT OF THIS KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOM,
TO PRESERVE THE RIGHTS &amp; LIBERTIES</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:118951:14"/>
               <hi>In the</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Walſingha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Stow, Hollin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, Speed, Grafton, Baker An. 5. R. 2. John Stows Survay of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. p. 89. 10 103. Mr. <hi>St. Iohns</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at Law, at <hi>Straffords</hi> Attainder, p. 14</note> 
               <hi>fifth year of</hi> King Richard the ſecond, <hi>the vulgar</hi>
Rabble of people and Villains, in Kent, Eſſex, Suſſex, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk,
Cambridgeſhire and other Countries, <hi>under the Conduct
of</hi> Wat Tyler, Jack Straw <hi>and other</hi> Rebels, <hi>aſſembling
together in great multitudes,</hi> reſolved by force and violence
to abrogate the Law of villenage, with all other Lawes they diſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
formerly ſettled; to burn all the Records, kill and behead
all the Judges, Juſtices, and men of Law of all ſorts, which they
could get into their hands; to burn and deſtroy the Innes of Court,
(as they did then the new Temple, where the apprentices of the
Law lodged, burning their Monuments and Records of Law
there found) to alter the tenures of Lands, to deviſe new Laws
of their own, by which the Subjects ſhould be governed, to change
the ancient Hereditary, Monarchicall Government of the Realm,
and to elect pettie elective Tyrannies and Kingdoms to themſelves
in every Shire: (<hi>a project eagerly proſecuted by ſome</hi> Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall
Anabaptiſts, and Jeſuites, Levellers, <hi>very lately: and
though withall</hi> they intended to deſtroy the King at laſt, and
all the Nobles too, when they had gotten ſufficient power, <hi>yet at
firſt to cloak their intentions for the preſent, they took</hi>
an Oath <hi>of all they met;</hi> Quod Regi &amp; communibus fidelita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem
ſervarent, <hi>that they ſhould keep Allegeance and faith
to the King and Commons, this their reſolution and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
thus to alter and</hi> ſubvert the Laws and Government,
<hi>upon full debate in the</hi> Parliament of 5 R. 2. n. 30, 31. was
declared to be <hi>HIGH TREASON</hi> againſt the King and againſt
the Law; <hi>for which divers of the chief actours in this</hi>
Treaſonable Deſign <hi>were condemned and executed, as Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,
in ſeverall places; and the reſt enforced</hi> to a publick
ſubmiſſion, <hi>and then pardoned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>In the</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Stow, Holin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, Graften, Baker in XI. 21. R. 2. and 1. H. 4. Satutes at large, 11. and 21 R. 2. &amp; 1. H. 4 M. <hi>St. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohns</hi> Speech concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony Judges, p. 28. to 37. And Argument at Law, at <hi>Straffords</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainder.</note> Parliament <hi>XL. R.</hi> 2. (<hi>as appears by the</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
Rolls <hi>and printed</hi> Statutes <hi>at large</hi>) three Prive Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellours,
the Archbiſhop of York, the Duke of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and
Earl of Suffolk; <hi>the Biſhop of</hi> Exeter <hi>the Kings Confeſſour,
five Knights, ſix Judges, (whereof Sir</hi> Robert Treſilian Chief
Juſtice <hi>was one</hi>) Blake <hi>of the Kings Councel at Law,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>sk
<hi>and others, were</hi> impeached and condemned of High Treaſon,
ſome of them executed as Traytors, the reſt baniſhed, their Lands
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118951:15"/>
and goods forfeited, and none to endevour to procure their pardon,
under pain of Felony; for endeavouring to overthrow a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
for the good of the Kingdome, and contrary to an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
of force of arms and Opinions in Law delivered to the
King, tending to ſubvert the Laws and Statutes of the Realm, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow
the Power, Priviledges, and proceedings of Parliament,
and betray (not all the houſe of Lords, <hi>but only</hi>) ſome of the
Lords of Parliament, <hi>which Judgement being afterwards
reverſed in the</hi> forced, and packed Parliament <hi>of 21. R. 2. was</hi>
reconfirmed <hi>in the</hi> Parliament <hi>of 1 H. 4. c. 3. 4, 5. and the</hi>
Parliament <hi>of 21. R.</hi> 2. totally repealed, and adnulled for ever, <hi>and
hath ſo continued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. <hi>In the</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Mr. St. John at Law againſt <hi>Straffords</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainder. p. 13. 14, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Parliament of 17 R. 2. n. 20. and Paſ.</hi> 17.
<hi>R. 2. B. RS. Ror. 16. Sir</hi> Thomas Talbot <hi>was accuſed and
found</hi> guilty of High Treaſon for conſpiring the death of the
Dukes of Gloceſter, Lancaſter and other Peers, who maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
the Commiſſion confirmed by act of Parliament, X. R. 2. and
aſſembling people in a warlike manner in the County of Cheſter,
for the effecting of it, in deſtruction of the Eſtates of the
Realm; <hi>and OF THE LAWES OF THE KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOME.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. In the 29. year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth, <hi>Jack Cade,</hi>
under a pretence to REFORM, <hi>alter, and abrogate ſome
Laws, Purveyances and extortions importable to the Commons</hi>
(wherupon he was called <hi>JOHN AMEND ALL</hi>) drew a
great multitude <hi>of Kentiſh people</hi> to <hi>Black Heath</hi> in a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
manner to effect it: in the <hi>Parliament</hi> of 29. H. 6. c. 1.
this was adjudged <hi>High Treaſon in him and his Complices;</hi> by
act of Parliament: and the <hi>Parliament</hi> of 31. H. 6. c. 1.
made this memorable Act againſt him, and his Imitators
inſucceeding ages; worth ſerious peruſall and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
by all who tread in his footſteps and over-act him
in his Treaſons.</p>
            <q rend="inline margQuotes">"<p>Whereas the moſt abominable Tyrant, horrible, odious, and
errant <hi>FALSE TRAITOR,</hi> John Cade, calling himſelf
ſometimes <hi>Mortimer,</hi> ſometime Captain of <hi>Kent, (which
Name,</hi> Fame, Acts and Feats, to be removed out of the ſpeech and
mind of every faithfull Chriſtian man, perpetually,) falſly and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118951:15"/>
trayterouſly purpoſing and imagining the perpetual deſtruction of
the KINGS PERSON and FINALL S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BVERSION
OF THIS REALM, taking upon him<note n="*" place="margin">And have not others of late aſſumed to themſelves, <hi>more Royal power than</hi> he? reſolved to be Treaſon by 21. <hi>E.</hi> 3. Rot. Parl. n. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>ROYALL
POWER,</hi> and gathering to him the Kings people in great
number, <hi>BY FALSE, SUBTIL, IMAGINED LAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GUAGE,</hi>
and ſeditiouſly made a ſtirring Rebellion, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDER COLO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R OF J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STICE FOR
REFORMATION OF THE LAWS OF THE SAID
KING, robbing, ſlaying, ſpoiling a great part of his faithfull
people: <hi>Our ſaid Soveraign Lord the King, conſidering
the premiſes with many other, which were more odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
to remember, by advice and aſſent of the Lords
ſpirituall and Temporall, and at THE REQUEST
OF THE COMMONS, and by authority aforeſaid,</hi>
hath ordained and eſtabliſhed, that the ſaid <hi>John</hi> Cade ſhall be
had named and declared <hi>A FALSE TRAYTOR</hi> to our
ſaid Soveraign Lord the King;<note place="margin">Nota.</note> 
                  <hi>and that all</hi> His Tyranny,
Acts, Facts, falſe Opinions, ſhall be voyded, abated, adnul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
deſtroyed, <hi>and</hi> put out of remembrance for ever. <hi>And
that</hi> all indictments in time coming, in like caſe under power of
Tyranny, Rebellion <hi>and</hi> ſtirring had, ſhall be of no regard, nor
effect, but void in Law: <hi>and all the Petitions</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">To wit by <hi>Cade</hi> and his confederates for the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> delivered
to the ſaid King in his laſt Parliament holden at <hi>Weſtminſter,
the ſixth day of</hi> November, <hi>the</hi> 29. of his Reign, againſt
his mind, by him not agreed, ſhall be taken and put in oblivion
out of remembrance, undone, voided, adnulled and deſtroyed,
for ever, as a thing purpoſed againſt God and his Conſcience,
and againſt his Royall eſtate and preheminence, and alſo DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RABLE
<hi>and</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NREASONABLE.</p>"</q>
            <p>5. In the<note n="a" place="margin">See Mr. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohns</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt <hi>Strafford,</hi> p. 178. Halls Chronicle and Hollinſhed.</note> 8 year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. <hi>William Bell,</hi>
and <hi>Thomas Lacy,</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent</hi> conſpired with
<hi>Thomas Cheyney</hi> (the Hermite of the <hi>Queen of Fairies)
TO OVERTHROW THE LAWS AND C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STOMES
OF THE REALM:</hi> for effecting whereof, they with
200. more met together, and concluded upon a cauſe or
raiſing greater forces in <hi>Kent,</hi> and the adjacent <hi>Shires,</hi> this
was <hi>adjudged high Treaſon,</hi> and ſome of them <hi>executed as
Traytors.</hi> Moreover, it<note n="b" place="margin">Cooks 3. inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, p. 9. 10.</note> 
               <hi>was reſolved by all the Judges of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118951:16"/>
in the reign of</hi> Henry 8. <hi>that an Inſurrection againſt the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute
of Labourers, or for the inhanſing of Salaries and wages
was TREASON, a levying war againſt the King,</hi> BECAUSE
IT WAS GENERALLY AGAINST THE KINGS
LAW, and the offendors took upon them THe RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORMATION
THEREOF, which <hi>Subjects by gathering
of power ought not to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Cooks 4. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes, ch. 8. p. 89. to 96.</note>6. On December 1. <hi>in the 21. year of King</hi> Henry
the 8. <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Moore, <hi>Lord Chancellour of</hi> England,
<hi>with 14. more, Lords of the Privy Councel,</hi> John Fitz-James,
Chief Juſtice of <hi>England, and Sir</hi> Anthony Fitzher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hert,
<hi>one of the</hi> Judges of the Common Pleas, <hi>exhibited ſundry
Articles of impeachment to King</hi> Henry the 8. <hi>againſt</hi>
Cardinall Wolſy: That he had by divers and many ſundry wayes
and faſhions committed High treaſon, <hi>and NOTABLE GRIE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VOUS
OFFENCES,</hi> miſuſing, <hi>Altering, and ſubverting
the order of his Graces Lawes,</hi> and otherwiſe; contrary to
his high Honour, Prerogative, Crown, Eſtate and Dignity
Royall; to the ineſtimable great hinderance, diminution and
decay of the uniuerſall Wealth of this his Graces Realm. <hi>The
Articles are 43. in number: The</hi> 20, 21, 26, 30, 35, 37, 42,
43. <hi>contain,</hi> his illegall, arbitrary practices and proceedings to
the ſubverſion of the due courſe and order of his Graces Lawes,
to the undoing of a great number of his loving people. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
they pray. Pleaſe therefore your moſt excellent Majeſty of your
excellent goodneſſe towards the Weal of this your Realm, and
Subjects of the ſame, to ſee ſuch order and direction upon the
ſaid Lord Cardinall, <hi>As may be to terrible example of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
to beware to offend your Grace,</hi> and <hi>your Lawes
hereafter:</hi> And that he be ſo provided for that he never have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Power, Jurisdiction or Authority hereafter, to trouble, vex,
or impoveriſh the Common wealth of this your Realm, as he
hoth done heretofore, to the great hurt and dammage of every
man almoſt, High and low. <note n="*" place="margin">See Speed, Holiſhed, Graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Stow, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitates Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae,</hi> Brit. p. 378. &amp; 379. and <hi>Goodwin</hi> in his life time.</note>
               <hi>His</hi> poyſoning <hi>himſelf prevented
his judgement for theſe his Practiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">M. <hi>St. Iohns</hi> Argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Strafford</hi>
               </note>7. The <hi>Statute of 1. Marie</hi> c. 12. Enacts that if 12. or more
ſhall endeavour <hi>By force to alter any of the Laws or Statutes
of the Kingdome;</hi> the offender ſhall from the time therein
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118951:16"/>
limited be adjudged ONELY AS A FELON: whereas it
was <hi>Treaſon</hi> before; but this Act continuing but till the
next <hi>Parliament,</hi> and then expiring, the offence remains
Treaſon, as before.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Cook 3 Inſt. c. 1. 9, 10. and M. <hi>St. Iohns</hi> Argument at Law, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Strafford</hi> p. 15, 16.</note>8. <hi>In the</hi> 39. <hi>of Queen</hi> Eliſabeth, <hi>divers in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of</hi> Oxford <hi>conſulted together, to</hi> go from Houſe to Houſe,
in that County, and from thence to <hi>London</hi> and other parts, to
excite them to take arms for the throwing down of incloſures
throughout the Realm; <hi>nothing more was proſecuted, nor
Aſſemblies made; yet</hi> in Eaſter Term 39. Eliſabeth, <hi>it was</hi>
reſolved by all the judges of <hi>England (who met about the
caſe) That this was</hi> High Treaſon, and a levying Warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the Queen, becauſe it was to throw down all incloſures
throughout the Kingdome, to which they could pretend no right,
and that the end of it was, to <hi>OVERTHROW THE LAWS
AND STATUTES for</hi> Incloſures. Whereupon <hi>BRAD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHAW
and BURTON (two of the principall offenders</hi>)
were condemned and executed at <hi>Aiciſton</hi> Hill in <hi>Oxfordſhire,
where they intended their firſt meeting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">See the Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of both Houſes, and Act for his Attainder, Mr. <hi>Pyms</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration upon the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Charge of High Treaſon againſt him, April the 12. 1641. M. <hi>St. Iohns</hi> Argument at Law at his Attainder, and <hi>Diurnal Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences.</hi>
               </note>9. <hi>To come nearer to our preſent times and caſe. In
the laſt</hi> Parliament of King <hi>Charls,</hi> Anno 1640. 1641. The
whole houſe of Commons impeached <hi>Thomas</hi> Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi>
Lord Deputy of <hi>Ireland</hi> of High Treaſon, amongſt other
<hi>Articles, for this crime eſpecially (wherein all the other
centred,</hi>) That he hath <hi>TREASONABLY ENDEVOU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RED</hi>
by his Words, Actions and Counſels, to <hi>SUBVERT THE
FUNDAMENTALL LAWS OF ENGLAND and IRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND,</hi>
and introduce an Arbitrary and Tyrannicall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<hi>This the whole</hi> Parliament <hi>declared and adjudged
to be</hi> High Treaſon, <hi>in and by their</hi> votes, and a ſpeciall
Act of Parliament for his Attainder; <hi>for which he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
and ſoon after executed on</hi> Tower Hill, <hi>as a</hi> Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour
to the King and Kingdome, <hi>May</hi> 22. 1641.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="c" place="margin">See the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and Lords <hi>Iournals,</hi> his printed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment, Mr. Pyms Speech thereat, <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buties</hi> Doom. p. 25, 26, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 38, 40<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>10. The <hi>whole Houſe of Commons</hi> the ſame <hi>Parliament</hi>
impeached <hi>William Laud Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury <hi>of</hi>
HIGH TREASON; in theſe very terms, <hi>February</hi> 6.
1640.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That he hath <hi>trayterouſly endeavoured to ſubvert
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118951:17"/>
Fundamentall Lawes and Government of this Kingdome
of</hi> England, and inſtead thereof to introduce <hi>An Arbitrary</hi>
and <hi>Tyrannicall Government againſt Law:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See chap. 2. Propoſition 1.</note>
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">
                  <p>"and he to that
end hath wickedly, <hi>and TRAYTEROUSLY</hi> adviſed his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,
that he might at his own will and pleaſure, L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vy and take
money of his Subjects without their conſent in Parliament, and
and this he affirmed was warrantable by the Law of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> He hath for the better accompliſhment of that his
Trayterous deſign, <hi>adviſed and procured Sermons and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Diſcourſes, to be preached, printed and publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi>
in which the Authority of Parliaments, and the force of
the Lawes of this Kingdome have been denyed, and abſolute
and unlimited Power over the perſons and eſtates of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties
Subjects maintained and defended, not onely in the King,
but in himſelf and other Biſhops againſt the Law.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>He hath by Letters, Meſſages, Threats
and promiſes, and by divers other wayes to Judges, and
other Miniſters of Juſtice, interrupted, perverted, and at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
times by means aforeſaid hath endevoured to interrupt and
pervert the courſe of Juſtice in his Majeſties Courts at</hi> Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter
<hi>and other Courts,</hi> TO THE SUBVERSION
OF THE LAWS OF THIS KINGDOME, whereby
ſundry of his Majeſties Subjects have been ſtopt in their
juſt ſuits, deprived of their lawfull Rights, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
to his Tyrannical will, to their ruine and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>That he hath trayterouſly endevoured to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
the other Courts of Juſtice,</hi> by a viſing and procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
his Majeſty to ſell places of Judicature, and other
offices, CONTRARY TO THE LAWS and CU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STOMES
in that behalf.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, He hath TRAYTEROUSLY cauſed a Book
of <hi>Canons</hi> to be compiled and publiſhed, without any
lawfull warrant and Authority in that behalf; <hi>in
which pretended Canons many matters are contained, contrary
to</hi> the Kings Prerogative, to the fundamentall Laws and
Statutes of this Realm, to the Rights of Parliament,
to the Property, and Liberty of the Subject, <hi>and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118951:17"/>
tending to ſedition and of dangerous conſequence; and to
the eſtabliſhing of a vaſt, unlawfull, preſumptuous power in
himſelf and his Succeſſors &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seventhly, That he hath trayterouſly endevored to <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
and ſubvert Gods true Religion BY LAW ESTABLISH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ED;</hi>
and inſtead thereof to ſet up Popiſh Religion and
Idolatry, And to that end hath declared, and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in Speeches and Printed Books, divers Popiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,
and opinions, contrary to to the Articles of
Religion, <hi>ESTABLISHED BY LAW.</hi> He hath urged
and enjoyned divers Popiſh, and Superſtitious Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
<hi>WITHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T ANY WARRANT OF LAW;</hi>
and <hi>hath cruelly perſecuted thoſe who have oppoſed the ſame, by
corporall puniſhments, and impriſonments; and moſt unjuſtly
vexed others who refuſed to conform thereunto by Ecccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall
Cenſures, Excommunication, Suſpenſion, Deprivation
and Degradation, CONTRARY TO THE LAWS OF
THIS KINGDOME.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>13. He did by his own authority and power contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
to Law <hi>procure</hi> ſundry of his Majeſties Subjects, and
enforced the Clergy of this Kingdome to contribute
towards the maintenance of the war againſt the <hi>Scots.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That to preſerve himſelf from being queſtioned for
theſe and other his Trayterous Courſes, he hath
laboured <hi>to Subvert the Rights of Parliament, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
Courſe of Parliamentary Proceedings,</hi> and by falſe and
malicious ſlanders to incenſe his Majeſty againſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments.</p>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>All which being proved againſt him at his Triall, were
after ſolemn Argum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt by Mr. <hi>Samuel Brown</hi> in behalf of
the Commons Houſe proved; and ſoon after adjudged,
to be <hi>High Treaſon at the Common Law,</hi> by <hi>both Houſes of
Parliament;</hi> and ſo declared in the <hi>Ordinance for his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainder:</hi>
for which he was <hi>condemned and beheaded</hi> as <hi>a Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
againſt the King, Law and Kingdome,</hi> on Tower hill, <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi>
10. 1644.</p>
            <p>11. In the<note n="a" place="margin">See the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and Lords Journals, Durnal Occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences p. 15, 16 19. 37. 191. to 264. and Mr. St. <hi>Iohns</hi> Speech at a conſcience of both Houſes of Parliament concerning ſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mony and theſe Judges. Together with the Speeches of Mr. <hi>Hide,</hi> Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi> Mr. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erpoint,</hi> Mr. <hi>Denzill Hollis,</hi> at their impeachments <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uly</hi> 16. 1641. aggravating their offences in Diurnall Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences and Speeches.</note> ſame <hi>Parliament, December</hi> 21. Jan. 14. Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary
11. 1640. and July 6. 1641. Sir <hi>John Finch,</hi> then
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118951:18"/>
Lord Keeper, chief Juſtice <hi>Bramſton,</hi> Judge <hi>Berkly,</hi> Judge
<hi>Crawly,</hi> Chief Baron <hi>Davenport,</hi> Baron <hi>Weſton,</hi> and Baron
<hi>Turnour,</hi> were accuſed and impeached by the Houſe of
Commons, by ſeveral <hi>Articles</hi> tranſmitted to the Lords,
OF HIGH TREASON, <hi>for that they had</hi> Traitorouſly <hi>and
wickedly endeavoured</hi> to ſubvert the Fundamentall Laws,
and eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bliſhed Government of the Realm of ENGLAND,
<hi>and inſtead thereof to introduce</hi> an Arbitrary and Tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
Government againſt Law; <hi>which they had declared by
Traiterous and wicked words, opinions, judgement, and more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially
in this their extrajudiciall opinion ſubſcribed by them in
the caſe of</hi> Ship-money, viz. <hi>We are of opinion, that when
the good and ſafety of the Kingdome in generall is concerned, and
the whole kingdome in danger; Your Majeſty may by Writ under
the Great Seal of</hi> England (without conſent in Parliament)
<hi>command all your Subjects of this your Kingdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See ch. 2. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition 1.</note> 
               <hi>at their charge
to provide and furniſh ſuch a number of Ships, with Men, Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
and Ammunition, and for ſuch time as your Majeſty ſhall think
fit, for the Defence and ſafeguard of the Kingdome, from ſuch
danger and perill. And we are of opinion, that in ſuch caſe, your
Majeſty is the ſole Judge both of the danger, and when, and how,
the ſame is to be prevented and avoided.</hi> And likewiſe for ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing
and giving iudgment accordingly in Maſter <hi>John
Hempdens</hi> caſe, in the <hi>Exchequer Chamber,</hi> in the point of
Ship money in <hi>Aprill 1638. which ſaid Opinions</hi> are De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive
to the Fundamental Laws of the Realm, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
Right of Propriety, <hi>and contrary to former Reſolutions
in Parliament,</hi> and the Petition of Right; <hi>as</hi> the words
of their ſeveral Impeachments run. Sr. <hi>John Finch</hi>
fled the Realm to <hi>preſerve his head on his Shoulders;</hi> ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
of them d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed through fear, to prevent the danger
ſoon after their <hi>Impeachments;</hi> and the reſt put to Fines,
who were leſſe peccant.</p>
            <p>12. Mr. <hi>John Pim,</hi> in his <hi>Declaration</hi> upon the whole
matter of the <hi>Charge</hi> of <hi>High Treaſon</hi> againſt <hi>Thomas</hi> Earle
of <hi>Strafford,</hi> April 12. 1641. before a <hi>Committee of both
Houſes of Parliament in Weſtminſter Hall; printed and publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by Order of the Houſe of Commons;</hi> proves his endeavour
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118951:18"/>
to ſubvert the <hi>Fundamentall Law of England,</hi> and to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
an Arbitrary Power; to be <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> and an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
very hainous in the nature, and miſchievous in the
effects thereof; which (ſaith he) will beſt appear, if it be
examined by that univerſall and ſupream Law, <hi>Salus Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li:</hi>
the element of all laws, out of which they are deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved:
the end of all Laws, to which they are deſigned, and
in which they are perfected.</p>
            <p>1. <q rend="inline margQuotes">
                  <p>'It is an offence comprehending all other offences.
Here you ſhall finde ſeveral Treaſons, Murthers, Rapins,
Oppreſſions, Perjuries. There is in this Crime, a Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
of all evills, hurtfull to a State; and if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
the Reaſons of it, it muſt needs be ſo. The Law,
is that which puts a difference betwixt Good and Evill:
betwixt juſt and unjuſt.<note place="margin">Nota.</note> If you take away the Law, all
things will fall into Confuſion; every man will become
a law to himſelf, which in the depraved condition of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
nature muſt needs produce man great enormities.
<note n="*" place="margin">And are they not ſo now?</note>Luſt will become a Law, and Envy will become a Law;
Covetouſneſſe and Ambition will become Laws; and
what Dictates, what deciſions ſuch laws will produce,
may eaſily be diſcerned in the late Governm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
(and <hi>England</hi> too ſince this.) The Law hath a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
to prevent, to reſtrain, to repair evils: without this
all kind of miſchiefs and diſtempers will break in upon
a State. It is the Law that doth the King to the Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
and Service of his people: it intitles the People to
the Protection and Juſtice of the King, &amp;c. <hi>The Law is
the Boundary, the meaſure betwixt the Kings Prerogative,
and the peoples Liberty, whiles theſe move in their own O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b,
they are a ſupport and ſecurity to one another: but if theſe
Bounds be ſo removed that they enter into conteſtation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict,
one of theſe miſchiefs muſt needs enſue. If the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
of the King overwhelm the Liberty of the people, it will be
turned into Tyranny: If Liberty undermine the Prerogative
it will turn into Anarchy. The Law is the ſafeguard, the cuſtody
of all private intereſts, your honours, your lives, your liberties,
and eſtates are all in the keeping of the Law, without this eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118951:19"/>
man hath a like Right to any thing: and this is the condition
into which the Iriſh were brought by the Earl of</hi> Strafford,
(and the Engliſh by others who condemned him.) And
the reaſon which he gave for it, hath more miſchief
than the thing it ſelf: THEY ARE A CONQUER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ED
NATION (Let thoſe who now ſay the ſame of
<hi>England,</hi> as well as <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> conſider and
obſerve what follows,) <hi>There cannot be a word more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnant
and fruitfull</hi> IN TREASON, <hi>then that word is.
There are few Nations in the world, that have not been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered,
and no doubt but the Conquerour may give what Laws
he pleaſe, to thoſe that are conquered. But if the ſucceeding
Acts and agreements do not limit and reſtrain that Right, what
people can be ſecure?</hi> England <hi>hath been conquered and</hi>
Wales <hi>hath been conquered; and by this reaſon will be in lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
better caſe than</hi> Ireland. <hi>If the King by the Right of a
Conquerour give Lawes to his people, ſhall not the people by the
ſame reaſon be reſtored to the Right of the conquered,</hi> To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
their Liberty if they can? What can be more hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
more pernicious than ſuch Propoſitions as
theſe?</p>
                  <p>2. It is dangerous to the Kings perſon: and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
to his Crown: It is apt to cheriſh Ambition, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation
and Oppreſſion in great men: and to beget
Sedition, Diſcontent in the people, and both theſe
have been, and in reaſon muſt ever be cauſes of great
Trouble and Alterations to Prince and State. If the
Hiſtories of thoſe Eaſtern Countries be peruſed, where
Princes order their Affairs according to the miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous
Principles of the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> LOOSE and
ABSOLVED FROM ALL RULES OF GOVERN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT;
they will be found to be frequent in combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions,
full of Maſſacres, and of the tragicall end of
Princes. If any man ſhall look into our own Stories in
the times,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> when the Laws were moſt neglected, he ſhall
find them full of Commotions, of Civil Diſtempers:
whereby the Kings that then raigned were alwayes
kept in want and diſtreſſe, the people conſumed with
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118951:19"/>
CIVIL WARRES: and by ſuch wicked Counſels as
theſe, ſome of our Princes have been brought to ſuch mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable
ends, <hi>As</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Note this all whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons-houſe Opinion then.</note> 
                     <hi>no honeſt heart can remember without hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi>
and <hi>earneſt Prayer, that it may never be ſo again.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. As it is dangerous to the Kings perſon and Crown,
ſo it is in other reſpects very prejudiciall to his Majeſty,
in honour, profit and greatneſſe (which he there proves
at large, as you may there read at leaſure) and yet theſe
are the Guildings and Paintings, that are put upon ſuch
Counſels: Theſe are for your Honour, for your
Service.</p>
                  <p>4. It is inconſiſtent with the Peace, the Wealth, the
Proſperity of a Nation. It is deſtructive to Juſtice,
the mother of Peace: to Induſtry, the Spring of Wealth;
to Valour, which is the active vertue, whereby the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity
of a Nation can onely be procured, confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
and enlarged. It is not onely apt to take a way Peace,
and ſo intangle the Nation with warres, but doth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
Peace, and powrs ſuch a malignity into it, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth
the effects of War: both to the<note n="*" place="margin">Is not this an experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall truth now.</note> NOBILITY
and others having as little ſecurity of THEIR PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SONS
OR ESTATES, in this peaceable time, as if the
Kingdome had been under the fury and rage of warre.
And as for Induſtry and Valour, who will take pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
for that, which when he hath gotten, is not his own?
or who fights for that wherein he hath no other intereſt,
but ſuch as is ſubject to the will of another? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
Shall it be Treaſon to embaſe the Kings Coin; though
but a piece of twelve pence or ſix pence, and muſt it not
needs be the effect of GREATER TREASON to
<note n="*" place="margin">And were they ever ſo baſe, cowardly, ſlaviſh as now?</note> embaſe the Spirits of his Subjects, and to ſet a ſtamp
and Character of Servitude upon them, whereby they
ſhall be diſabled to do any thing for the Service of the
King or Common-wealth?</p>
                  <p>5. In times of ſudden danger, by the Invaſion of an
enemy, it will diſable his Majeſty to preſerve himſelf and
his Subjects from that danger. When war threatens a
Kingdome, by the coming of a forreign enemy, it is no
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118951:20"/>
time then to diſcontent the people, to make them wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of the PRESENT GOVERNMENT, and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable
to a change. The Supplies which are to come
in this way, will be unready, uncertain; there can be
no aſſurance of them, no dependence upon them, either
for time or proportion. And if ſome money be gotten
in ſuch a way, the Diſtractions, the Diviſions, Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
which this cauſe is apt to produce, will be more
prejudiciall to the publick ſafety, than the Supply can
be advantageous to it.</p>
                  <p>6. This crime is contrary to the Pact and Covenant between the
King and his people; by mutuall agreement and ſtipulation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
by OATH on both ſides.</p>
                  <p>7. It is an Offence that is contrary to the ends of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
                  <p>1. To prevent Oppreſſions; to<note n="*" place="margin">Was ever their power, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded in all Kinds as now?</note> limit and reſtrain the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive
power and violence of great Men: to open paſſages of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
with indifference towards all.</p>
                  <p>2. To preſerve men in their Eſtates, to ſecure them in their
Lives, and Liberties.</p>
                  <p>3. That vertue ſhould be cheriſhed, and vice ſuppreſſed: but
where Laws are ſubverted, and arbitrary and unlimited power
ſet up; a way is open not onely for the ſecurity, but for the
Advancement and Incouragement of evil. Such men as are
<note n="*" place="margin">Is it not moſt true of late and ſtill?</note> apteſt for the execution and maintenance of this power are
onely capable of Preferment, and others, will not he Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of any unjuſt Commands, who make conſcience to do any
thing againſt the Law of the Kingdome,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> and Liberties of the
Subject, are not only not paſſable for imployment; <hi>but SUBJECT
TO MUCh JEALOUSIE and DANGER, (Is not this
their Condition of late and preſent times?</hi> expertus lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor.)</p>
                  <p>4. That all Accidents and events, all Counſels, and Deſigns
ſhould be improved to the publick good. But this arbitrary power
is apt to diſpoſe all to the maintenance of it ſelf. <hi>And is it not
ſo now?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>8. The Treaſons of Suberſions of the Lawes, violation of
Liberties can never be good or juſtifiable by any circumſtance or
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118951:20"/>
occaſion, being evil in their own nature, how ſpecious or good ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
they be pretended. He alledgeth it was a time of <hi>GREAT
NECESSITY and DANGER,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Nota.</note> when ſuch Counſels were
neceſſary <hi>FOR THE PRESERVATION OF THE
STATE, (the Plea ſince, and now uſed by others, who
condemned him:</hi>) If there were any <hi>NECESSITY IT
WAS OF HIS OWN MAKING.</hi> He by his evil Counſel
had brought the King (<hi>as others the Kingdome ſince</hi>) into
a neceſſity; and by no Rules of Juſtice can be allowed to gain
this advantage to his Juſtification; which is <hi>A GREAT
PART OF HIS OFFENCE.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>9. As this is Treaſon in the nature of it, ſo it doth
exceed all other Treaſons in this; that in the Deſign
and endevour of the Authour, it was to be A CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STANT
and PERMANENT TREASON; a ſtanding,
perpetual Treaſon, which would have been in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
Act, not determined within one time or age, but
tranſmitted to Poſterity, even from Generation to Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.
And are not others Treaſons of late times
ſuch, proclaimed ſuch, in and by their own <hi>Printed Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi>
and therein exceeding <hi>Straffords?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>10. As it is a crime <hi>Odious</hi> in the nature of it, ſo it is
odious in the Judgement and eſtimation of the Law.
TO ALTER THE SETLED FRAME AND CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STITUTION
OF GOVERNMENT IN ANY
STATE. (Let thoſe conſider it who are guilty of it in
the higheſt Degree, beyond <hi>Strafford, Canterbury,</hi> or the
<hi>Shipmony Judges</hi> in our own State) The Lawes whereby
all parts of a Kingdome are preſerved, ſhould be very
vain and defective, if they had not a <hi>Power to ſecure and
preſerve themſelves.</hi> The <hi>Forfeitures</hi> inflicted for <hi>Treaſon</hi> by
our <hi>Law,</hi> are of <hi>Life, Honour</hi> and <hi>Eſtate,</hi> even all that
can be forfeited: and this <hi>Priſoner,</hi> although he ſhould
<note n="*" place="margin">And others, as well as he, of farre inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour place and Eſtate.</note> pay all theſe <hi>Forfeitures,</hi> will ſtill be a <hi>Debtor</hi> to the
<hi>Common wealth.</hi> Nothing can be more equall, <hi>then that he
ſhould periſh by the Juſtice of the Law, which he would have
ſubverted.</hi> Neither will this be a <hi>New way of blood.</hi> There
are marks enough to trace this <hi>Law</hi> to the very Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118951:21"/>
of this Kingdome. And if it hath not been put in
execution, as he alledgeth this 240 years; it was not
for <hi>want of Law,</hi> but that all <hi>that time had not bread a man</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">But have not our times bred men much bolder then he, ſince this Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ech was made, and he executed.</note> 
                     <hi>bold enough to commit ſuch crimes as theſe:</hi> which is a
<hi>circumſtance</hi> much aggravating his <hi>Offence,</hi> and making
him no leſſe liable to puniſhment, becauſe he is THE
<note n="*" place="margin">Since he hath many follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s.</note> ONELY MAN, that in ſo long a time hath ventured
UPON SUCH A TREASON AS THIS.'</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far M. <hi>John Pym;</hi> in the <hi>Name</hi> and by the <hi>Order</hi> and
<hi>Authority</hi> of the whole <hi>Commons Houſe</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I
wiſh all thoſe, who by their <hi>Words, Actions, Counſels</hi> (and
printed <hi>Publications</hi> too, <hi>have trayterouſly endevoured to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
the Fundamentall Lawes, Liberties of</hi> England and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
and to introduce an arbitrary and Tyrannicall Government
againſt Law,</hi> as much as ever <hi>Strafford</hi> did, and out ſtripped
him therein, (even ſince his execution) in all particulars,
for which he was <hi>beheaded;</hi> would now ſeriouſly lay to
heart, and ſpeedily reform, leſt they equall or exceed him
in concluſion, in <hi>Capitall puniſhments</hi> for the ſame, or end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,
<hi>Helliſh Torments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Authority I ſhall produce in point is, <hi>The
ſpeech and Declaration</hi> of Mr. <hi>Oliver St. John</hi> at a Conference
of both <hi>Houſes of Parliament,</hi> concerning <hi>Shipmony</hi> upon
Judge <hi>Finches Impeachment of High Treaſon,</hi> January 14.
1640. printed by the <hi>Commons Order, London,</hi> 1641. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
he <hi>declares the ſenſe of the Commons.</hi> p. 12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">
                  <p>'<hi>That by the
Judges Opinions</hi> (forecited) <hi>concerning Shipmony</hi> THE
FUNDAMENTAL LAWS OF THE REALM CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CERNING
OUR PROPERTY and OUR PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SONS
ARE SHAKEN. <hi>Whoſe Treaſonable Offence</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
he thus aggravates. <hi>p. 20. &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Judges</hi> as is declared
in the Parliament of 11. <hi>R.</hi> 2. are the <hi>Executors</hi> of the <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,
and of the Judgements and Ordinances of Parliament.</hi>
They have here made themſelves the<note n="*" place="margin">Have none done ſo ſince them.</note> 
                     <hi>EXEC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TIONERS
OF THEM;</hi> they have endevoured <hi>THE DESTR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CTION
OF THE F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDAMENTALS OF O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R LAWS
and LIBERTIES. Holland</hi> in the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> lies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the Sea: the <hi>Superficies</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> is lower than
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118951:21"/>
the <hi>Superficies</hi> of the <hi>Sea.</hi> It is <hi>Capitall</hi> therefore for any
man to cut the <hi>Banks,</hi> becauſe they defend the Country.
Beſides our own,<note place="margin">See chap. 2.</note> even Forreign Authours, as <hi>Comines</hi>
obſerves,<note place="margin">Propoſition 1.</note> That the Statute <hi>DE TALLAGIO,</hi> and the
other <hi>old Laws</hi> are the <hi>Sea walls</hi> and <hi>Banks,</hi> which keep
the Commons from the innundation of the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.
Theſe<note n="*" place="margin">Aave not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pioners and Jaſſes done the like?</note> 
                     <hi>Pioners</hi> have not onely <hi>undermined</hi> theſe
<hi>Banks,</hi> but they have <hi>levelled</hi> them even with the ground.
It one that was known to be <hi>Hoſtis Patriae,</hi> had done this,
though the <hi>Dammage</hi> be the ſame, yet the <hi>Guilt</hi> is leſſe;
but the <hi>Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ervatores Riparum,</hi> the overſeers intruſted
with the Defence of theſe <hi>Banks,</hi> for them to deſtroy
them; the <hi>breach of Truſt</hi> aggravates, nay alters the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of the offence. <hi>Breach of Truſt</hi> though in a private
Perſon, and in the leaſt things, is <hi>odious amongſt all men:</hi>
much more in a publick Perſon, in things of great and
publick concernment, becauſe<note n="*" place="margin">This is now grown a meere Paradox.</note> GREAT TRUST
BINDS THE PARTY TRUSTED TO GREAT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>EST
CARE AND FIDELITY.</p>
                  <p>It is TREASON in the <hi>Conſtable of Dover Caſtle</hi> to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
the Keys to the known enemies of the Kingdom, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
the <hi>Caſtle is the Key of the Kingdome:</hi> wheras if the
houſekeeper of a private perſon, deliver poſſeſſion to his
Adverſary, it is a crime ſcarce puniſhab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e by Law. The
<note n="*" place="margin">What are they now of late times of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Changes?</note> 
                     <hi>Judges</hi> under his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> are the Perſons truſted with
the Laws and in them with the <hi>Lives, Liberties and Eſtates
of the whole Kingdom.</hi> This Truſt of all we have, is prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
from his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> &amp;<note n="*" place="margin">See 27 H. 8. c. 24. 26. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gna Charta. c. 12. 29 32 H. 3. c. 1. 3, 5. 9, 20 3 E. 1 c. 44. 45, 46. 13 E. 1. 10, 12 30 31. 35, 39. 44. 45. 25 E 1. c. 1, 2. 27 E., 1. c. 2, 3. 34 E. 1. c. 6. 12 E. 2. c. 6. 2 E. 3. c. 3. 14 E. 3. c. 10. 16. Rastal Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices.</note> in him delegated to the <hi>Judges.</hi>
His <hi>Majeſty</hi> at his <hi>Coronation</hi> is bound by his <hi>Oath</hi> TO
EXECUTE JUSTICE TO HIS PEOPLE ACCOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DING
TO THE LAWS, thereby to aſſure the people
of the faithfull performance of his <hi>Great Truſt:</hi> His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
again, as he truſts the <hi>Judges</hi> with the performance
of this part of his <hi>Oath;</hi> ſo doth he likewiſe exact ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>Oath</hi> of them, for their due execution of Juſtice to
the people, according to the Laws: hereby the Judges
ſtand intruſted with this part of his <hi>Majeſties Oath.</hi> If
therefore the <hi>Judges</hi> ſhall do wittingly againſt the Law,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118951:22"/>
they do not onely break their <hi>own Oaths,</hi> and therein the
<hi>Common Faith and Truſt of the whole Kingdome,</hi> but do as
much as in them lies, ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rce and blemiſh the ſacred
Perſon of his <hi>Majeſty</hi> with the odious and hatefull ſin of
<note n="*" place="margin">Was it ever ſo freque <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t a ſia as now in all ſorts of late Judges, Officers Subjects?</note> 
                     <hi>Perjury.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Lords,</hi> the hainouſneſſe of this offence is moſt le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible
in the<note n="*" place="margin">Do none de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve as ſevere now?</note> ſevere puniſhment which former ages have
inflicted upon thoſe <hi>Judges,</hi> who have broken any part
of their <hi>Oaths</hi> wittingly, though in things not ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
to the Subject, as in the caſe in queſtion.<note n="*" place="margin">See Cooks 3. Instil. p. 146, 147<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and f. 133 Hollirſhed p. 284, 285. Speeds Hiſtory p. 651. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ow, Walſingham, Daniel in 18 Ed. 1.</note> Sir
<hi>Thomas Wayland,</hi> Chief Juſtice of the <hi>Common-Pleas, 17 E.</hi>
1. was attainted of <hi>Felony for taking bribes,</hi> and his <hi>Lands</hi>
and <hi>Goods forfeited,</hi> as appears in the <hi>Pleas of Parliament,</hi>
18 E. 1. and <hi>he was baniſhed the Kingdome,</hi> as unworthy to
live in the State againſt which he had ſo much offended.
<note n="*" place="margin">See Cgoks 3. Instit. p. 145.</note> Sir <hi>William Thorp</hi> Chief Juſtice of the <hi>Kings Bench</hi> in <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi>
the thirds time, having of five perſons received
five ſeverall <hi>Bribes,</hi> which in all amounted to one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
pounds, was for this alone, <hi>adjudged to be hanged, and
all his Goods and Lands forfeited:</hi> The reaſon of the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
is entered in the Roll in theſe words. <hi>Quia praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus
Wilielmus</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Have none of this Name, or of his Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſince done the like in an higher degree?</note> 
                     <hi>Thorp qui Sa cramentum Domini Regis erga
populum ſuum habuit ad cuſtodiendum, fugit malitiosè falsò &amp;
rebelliter, quantum in ipſo fuit.</hi> There is a notable Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
in that Judgement, that this Judgement was not
to be drawn into example, againſt any other officers,
who ſhould break their Oaths, but onely againſt thoſe,
<hi>qui praedictum Sacramentum fecerunt, &amp; fregerunt, &amp;</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Let Custodes Legum &amp; Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rtatum Angliae remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber it.</note> 
                     <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent
Leges Angliae ad cuſtodiendum:</hi> That is onely to the
<hi>Judges Oaths,</hi> who have the Laws intruſted unto them.
This Judgement was given 24 E. 3. The next year in
Parliament 25 E. 3. <hi>Num.</hi> 10. it was debated in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
whether this Judgement was legall? <hi>Et nullo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicente,</hi>
it was declared, TO BE JUST AND AC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CORDING
TO THE LAW: <hi>and that the</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Let the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pater and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it.</note> 
                     <hi>ſame Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
may be given in time to come upon the like occaſion.</hi> This
caſe is in point, <hi>That it is death for any Judge wittingly, to
break his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ath in any part of it.</hi> This <hi>oath</hi> of <hi>Thorp</hi> is entred in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118951:22"/>
the Roll, and is the ſame <hi>verbatim</hi> with the Judges <hi>Oath</hi>
in 18 E. 3. <hi>and is the ſame which the Judges now take.</hi> (And
let thoſe who have taken the ſame Oath, remember and
apply this Preſident, left others do it for them.)</p>
                  <p>Your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> will give me leave to obſerve the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences
between that and the caſe in queſtion.</p>
                  <p>1. That of <hi>Thorp,</hi> was onely a ſelling of the <hi>Law</hi> by
<hi>Retail</hi> to thoſe five perſons, for he had five ſeverall
bribes, of theſe five perſons; the Paſſage of the Law to
the reſt of the Subjects for ought appears, was free and
open. But theſe <hi>Opinions</hi> are a conveyance of the <hi>Law</hi> by
<hi>wholeſale,</hi> and that not to, but from the Subject.</p>
                  <p>2. In that of <hi>Thorp.</hi> as to thoſe five perſons, it was
not an <hi>abſolute deniall of Juſtice,</hi> it was not a <hi>damming
up,</hi> but a <hi>ſtraitning onely of the Chanel.</hi> For whereas the
<hi>Judges</hi> ought <hi>Judicium reddere,</hi> that is, the Laws being
<hi>THE BIRTHRIGHT and INHERITANCE OF THE
S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BJECT,</hi> the Judge when the parties in ſuit demand
Judgement, ſhould <hi>re dare,</hi> freely reſtore the Right unto
them; now he doth not <hi>dare,</hi> but <hi>vendere,</hi> with hazard
onely of perverting Juſtice; for the party that buyes the
Judgement, may have a good and honeſt cauſe. But
theſe <hi>Opinions,</hi> beſides that they have coſt the Subjects
very dear, dearer than any, nay, I think I may truly ſay,
than all the unjuſt Judgements that ever have been given
in this Realm, witneſſe the many hundred thouſand
pounds, which under colour of them have been levyed
upon the Subjects, amounting to<note n="*" place="margin">This is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon to the late Taxes, or Exciſes impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, without a Parliament a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 20 times as much as the Kings Shipmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and more frequent, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant, and endleſſe than it</note> ſeven hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
pounds and upwards, that have been paid unto the
<hi>Treaſurer</hi> of the Nav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, (in ſundry years) beſides what the
Subjects have been forced to pay Sheriffes, Sheriffes-Bayliffes,
(<hi>and now an hundred times more to T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oopers, and
Souldiers, who forcibly levy their unlawfull Contributions, and
Exciſes</hi>) and otherwiſe; which altogether as is concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
amounts not to leſſe than <hi>a million</hi> (in five years
ſpace, whereas now we pay above two Millions in Taxes,
Impoſts, Exciſes, every year) beſides the infinite v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of the Subject by ſuits in Law, binding them over,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118951:23"/>
attendance at the Councel Table, taking them from
their neceſſary imployments, in making Seſſes, and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections,
and impriſonment of their perſons (all now
trebled to what then) I ſay beſides what is paſt, to make
our miſeries compleat, they have as much as in them is
MADE THEM ENDLESSE (as others ſince have done)
for by theſe <hi>Opinions</hi> they have put upon themſelves and
their Succeſſors, <hi>An impoſſibility of ever doing us right again,
&amp; an incapacity upon us of demanding it ſo long as they continue</hi>
(as the Compilers of the late <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> with 42. Strings,
intitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed, <hi>The Government of the Common-wealth of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
<hi>&amp;c. Artic.</hi> 1, 2, 3, 9, 10, 12, 22, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28. 31, 32.
36, 37, 38, 39. have done, as far as they, and much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
them.)</p>
                  <p>In that ſore famine in the <hi>Land of Egypt,</hi> when the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants
were reduced to the next doore to death (for
there they ſay, why ſhould we die?) for bread, Firſt
they give their money, next their flocks and Cattle, laſt
of all their perſons and Lands for bread; all became
<hi>Pharaohs;</hi> but by this <hi>Lex Regia,</hi> there is a tranſaction
made, not onely of our perſons, but of our bread like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
wherewith our perſons ſhould be ſuſtained; that
was for bread, this of our bread. For ſince theſe <hi>Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
if we have any thing at all, we are not at all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding
TO THE LAW FOR IT, but are wholly
caſt UPON THE MERCY and GOODNESSE OF
THE KING. Again, there the <hi>Egyptians</hi> themſelves, ſold
themſelves, and all they had to the King, if ours had
been ſo done; if it had been ſo done by <hi>our own free conſent
in Parliament,</hi> we had the leſſe cauſe to complain: <hi>But it
was done againſt our wills,</hi> and <hi>by thoſe who were truſted,</hi> and
<hi>that upon Oath, with the preſervation of theſe things for us.</hi>
The Laws are our <hi>Forts,</hi> and <hi>Bulwarks</hi> of Defence: If the
Captain of a <hi>Caſtle,</hi> onely out of fear and Cowardice,
and not from any <hi>Compliance</hi> with the enemy ſurrender
it, This is TREAON, as was adjudged in Parliament,
1 R. 2. in the two Caſes of <hi>Comines</hi> and <hi>Weſton,</hi> and in
the Caſe of the Lord <hi>Gray,</hi> for ſurrendering <hi>Barwick</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118951:23"/>
to the <hi>Scots,</hi> in <hi>Edward</hi> the thirds time, though good
defence had been made by him, and that he had loſt his
eldeſt ſon in maintenance of the Siege: and yet the loſſe
of a <hi>Caſtle</hi> loſeth not the Kingdome, onely the place and
adjacent parts, with trouble to the whole. But by the
<hi>Opinions,</hi> there is a Surrender made <hi>of all our Legal defence
of Property:</hi> that which hath been preacht is now <hi>judged;</hi>
that there is no <hi>Meum &amp; Tuum, between the King and people;</hi>
beſides that which concerns our Perſons.</p>
                  <p>The Law is the <hi>Temple,</hi> the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> whether Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
ought to run for <hi>ſhelter</hi> and <hi>Refuge:</hi> hereby it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<hi>Templum fine numine,</hi> as was the <hi>Temple</hi> built by the
<hi>Romane Emperour,</hi> who after he had built it, put no <hi>gods</hi>
into it. We have the <hi>Letter</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> ſtill, but not the
<hi>ſenſe:</hi> we have the <hi>Fabrick of the Temple</hi> ſtill, but the <hi>Dii
Tutelares</hi> are gone. But this is not all the Caſe, that is,
<hi>That the Law now ceaſeth to aid and defend us in our Rights,</hi>
for then poſſeſſion alone were a good Title, if there were
no Law to take it away: <hi>Occupanti concederetur, &amp; melior
eſſet Poſſidentis conditio:</hi> But this, though too bad is not
the worſt: for beſides that which is <hi>Privitive</hi> in theſe <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions,</hi>
there is ſomewhat <hi>poſitive. For now the Law doth
not onely not defend us, but the Law it ſelf,</hi> (by temporiſing
Judges and Lawyers) <hi>is made the Inſtrument of taking all
away.</hi> For whenſoever his <hi>Majeſty</hi> or his <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> ſhall
be pleaſed to ſay, <hi>that the good and ſafety of the Kingdome
is concerned, and that the whole Kingdome is in danger, the
when and how, the ſame is to be prevented, makes our perſons and
all we have liable to bare will and Pleaſure.</hi> By this means,
<hi>The Sanctuary is turned into a Shambles; the Forts are ſleight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi>
that ſo they might neither do us good nor hurt; <hi>But
they are held againſt us by thoſe who ought to have held them for
us,</hi> and <hi>the mouth of our own Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n is turned upon our own
ſelves:</hi> and that by our own military Officers, Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
and others ſince, as well as the Ship money Judges
then)'</p>
               </q> 
Thus far Mr. <hi>Oliver St. John</hi> (by the Commons
Order) whoſe words I thought fit thus to tranſcribe at
large, becauſe not onely moſt pertinent, but <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118951:24"/>
the preſent times; wherein as in a Looking Glaſſe, ſome
pretended Judges and Grandees, of theſe preſent and late
paſt times, may behold their own faces and deformities;
and the whole Nation their ſad condition under them.
In the reſidue of that his Printed <hi>Speech,</hi> he compares the
<hi>Treaſon</hi> of the <hi>Shipmony Judges,</hi> and of Sir <hi>Robert Treſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium</hi>
and his Complices in XI. R. 2. condemned and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted
for Traytors by Judgement in Parliament, <hi>for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devouring
to ſubvert the lawes and ſtatutes of the Realm by their
illegall Opinions then delivered to King</hi> Richard <hi>at</hi> Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham
<hi>Caſtle,</hi> not out of <hi>conſpiracy,</hi> but for <hi>fear of death</hi> and
corporall <hi>Torments</hi> wherewith they were menaced:
whoſe offence he there makes tranſcendent to theirs then
in ſix particulars, as thoſe who pleaſe may there read at
leiſure, being over large to tranſcribe, I could here inform
you, that the Fundamentall laws of our Nation, are the
ſame in the Body politique of the Realm, as the Arteries,
Nerves, Veins, are in, and to the naturall Body, the Bark
to the tree; the Foundation to the Houſe: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the cutting of them aſunder, or their Subverſion,
muſt of neceſſity, kill, deſtroy, disjoyn and ruine the
whole Realm at once: therefore it muſt be Treaſon in the
higheſt degree. But I ſhall onely ſubjoyn here ſome mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall
Paſſages, in his <hi>Argument at Law,</hi> concerning the <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainder
of high Treaſon, of</hi> Thomas <hi>Earl of</hi> Strafford, <hi>before
a Committee of both Houſes of Parliament in</hi> Weſtminſter <hi>Hall,</hi>
April 29. 1641. ſoon after <hi>printed and publiſhed by Order of
the Commons Houſe:</hi> wherein <hi>p.</hi> 8. he layes down this Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
recited again, p. 64.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That</hi> (Straffords) <hi>Endeavouring</hi> To ſubvert the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall
Laws and Government of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi>
and inſtead thereof to introduce a Tyrannicall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
againſt Law, is Treaſon by the Common-Law.
<hi>That Treaſons at the Common-Law, are not taken away
by the Statutes,</hi> by 25. E. 3. 1. H. 4. c. 10. 1. Mar. c. 1. nor any
of them.</p>
            <p>The Authorities, Judgements, in and out of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
which he cites to prove it, have been already men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118951:24"/>
with ſome others he omitted; I ſhall therefore but
tranſcribe his Reaſons to evince it to be <hi>Treaſon,</hi> ſuper-added
to thoſe alledged by him againſt the <hi>Shipmony
Judges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 12. <hi>It is a Warre againſt the King</hi> (Let our Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary
Officers and ſouldiers conſider it) <hi>when</hi> intended.
<hi>The alteration of the laws or Government in any part of them.</hi>
This is a levying Warre againſt the King (and ſo <hi>Treaſon</hi>
within the Statute of 25 E 3.)</p>
            <p>1. Becauſe the King doth maintain and protect the laws in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
part of them.</p>
            <p>2. Becauſe they are the Kings laws. He is the Fountain from
whence in their ſeverall Channells, they are derived to the
Subject. Whence all our indictments run thus: Treſpaſſes laid to be
done, Contra pacem Domini Regis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> againſt the Kings Peace
for exorbitant offences; though not intended againſt the Kings
Perſon; againſt the King his Crown and dignity.</p>
            <q rend="inline margQuotes">'<p>Page 64. In this I ſhall not labour at all to prove,
That the endevouring by words, Counſels and actions,
<hi>To ſubvert the Fundamentall Laws and Government of the
Kingdome is Treaſon at the Common Law.</hi> If there be any
Common Law Treaſons at all left, NOTHING TREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SON
IF THIS NOT, TO MAKE A KINGDGME
NO KINGDOME. Take the Polity and Government
away, <hi>England's</hi> but a piece of earth, wherein ſo many
men have their commerce and abode, without rank or
diſtinction of men, without property in any thing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
than in poſſeſſion; no Law to puniſh the murdering,
or robbing one another.</p>'</q>
            <q rend="inline margQuotes">'<p>Page 70, 71, 72. <hi>The horridneſſe of the offence in endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring
to overthrow the Lawes and preſent Government,</hi> hath
been fully opened before. The <hi>Parliament</hi> is the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation
of the whole Kingdome, wherein <hi>The King as
Head, your Lordſhips as the more Noble,</hi> and <hi>the Commons,
the other Members are knit together in one body Politick.</hi> This
diſſolved, the Arteries and Ligaments that hold the body
together, THE LAWES. He that takes away the Laws,
takes not away the Allegiance of one Subject onely, but
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118951:25"/>
of the whole Kingdome. It was made <hi>Treaſon</hi> by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute
of 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> for her time to affirm, <hi>That the Lawes
of the Realme doe not bind the deſcent of the Crown.</hi> No
Law, no deſcent at all, NO LAWES NO PEERAGE,
no ranks nor degrees of men, the ſame condition to all.
Its <hi>Treaſon</hi> to kill a Judge upon the Bench; this kills not
<hi>Judicem ſed J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DICI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M.</hi> There be twelve men, but no
Law; never a Judge amongſt them. <hi>Its felony</hi> to embe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zel
any one of the Judiciall Records of the Kingdome:
<hi>THIS AT ONCE SWEEPS THEM ALL AWAY and
FROM ALL.</hi> Its <hi>Treaſon</hi> to countefeit a twenty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
piece: here's a counter feiting of the Law: we can
call neither the counterfeit nor the true coin our own.
Its <hi>Treaſon</hi> to counterfeit the Great Seal for an Acre of
Land: No property is left hereby to any Land at all,
<hi>Nothing Treaſon now, againſt King or Kingdome; No Law to
puniſh it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Lords, if the Queſtion were asked in <hi>Weſtminſter
Hall,</hi> whether this were a Crime puniſhable in <hi>Star cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi>
or in THE KINGS BENCH, by Fine or impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?
They would ſay, <hi>It were higher.</hi> If whether Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony?
They would ſay, That is an offence onely againſt
the life or goods of ſome one, or few perſons. It would
I believe be anſwered by the <hi>Judges,</hi> as it was by the
Chief Juſtice <hi>Thirning,</hi> in 21 R<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. <hi>That though he could not
judge the Caſe TREASON there before him, yet if he were a
Peer in Parliament; HE WO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD SO ADJ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DGE IT.</hi>
(And ſo the Peeres did here in <hi>Straffords,</hi> and not long
after in <hi>Canterburies</hi> Caſe, who both loſt their Heads on
Tower Hill.)</p>'</q>
            <p>I have tranſcribed theſe Paſſages of Mr. <hi>Oliver St. John</hi>
at large for five Reaſons.</p>
            <p>1. Becauſe they were the voice and ſenſe of the whole
Houſe of Commons by his mouth; who afterwards own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and ratified them by their ſpeciall Order for their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication
in print, for information and ſatisfaction of the
whole Nation, and terrour of all others who ſhould af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
that, either ſecretly or openly, by fraud or force, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:118951:25"/>
or indirectly, attempt the ſubverſion of all, or any
of our Fundamentall Laws, or Liberties, or the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of our Fandamentall Government, or ſetting up
any arbitrary or Tyrannicall power, Taxes, Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
or new kinds of arbitrary Judicato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments
againſt theſe our Laws and Liberties.</p>
            <p>2. To mind an inform all ſuch who have not only equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
but tranſcended <hi>Strafford</hi> and <hi>Canterbury</hi> in theſe their
<hi>High Treaſons,</hi> even ſince theſe <hi>Publications, Speeches,</hi> and
their <hi>exemplary executions,</hi> of the hainouſneſſe, in excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe,
wilfulneſſe, maliciouſneſſe, Capitalneſſe of
their crimes; which not onely the whole Parliament in
generality, but many of themſelves in particular, ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely
proſecuted, condemned, and inexorably puniſhed
of late years in them: that ſo they may bewail, repent
of, and reform them with all ſpeed and diligence, as much
as in them lies. And withall, I ſhall exhort them ſeriouſly
to conſider that Goſpel terrifying Paſſage, Rom. 2. 1, 2,
3. <hi>Therefore thou art inexcuſable O man, whoſoever thou art
that judgeſt; for wherein thou judgeſt another, tbou</hi> CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEMNEST
THY SELF; FOR THOU THAT JUD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GEST,
DOEST THE SAME THINGS. <hi>But we are ſure
that the judgement of God is according to truth, againſt them
which commit ſuch things. And thinkeſt thou this, O man, that
judgeſt them which do ſuch things, and doeſt the ſame, that thou
ſhalt eſcape the Judgement of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. To excite all Lawyers, eſpecially ſuch who of late
times have taken upon them the ſtile and power of Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
to examine their conſciences, actions, how far all
or any of them have been guilty of theſe crimes and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
ſo highly aggravated, and exemplarily puniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d
of former and later times, in corrupt, cowardly time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving,
degenerate Lawyers and <hi>Judaſſes,</hi> rather than
<hi>Judges,</hi> to the diſgrace of their Profeſſion, and prejudice
of the Fundamentall Lawes, Liberties, Rights, Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
of our Nation, Peers, Parliaments, ſubverſion of the
Fundamentall Government of this famous Kingdome,
whereof they are Members.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:118951:26"/>
4. To inſtruct thoſe <hi>Jeſuited Anabaptiſts, Levellers</hi> and
their Factors, (eſpecially <hi>John Canne,</hi> and the reſt of the
Compilers, Publiſhers, Abetters of the Pamphlet inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled,
<hi>Lieutenant Colonel Lilburn, tried and caſt,</hi> and other
forementioned publications:) who profeſſedly ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
by words, writing, Counſels and overt Acts to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
both our old Fundamentall (and all other Laws) Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,
Cuſtomes, Parliaments, and Government, what
tranſcendent <hi>Malefactor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, traytors and Enemies they are to the
publick,</hi> and what <hi>Capitall puniſhments,</hi> they may thereby
incurre, as well as demerit, ſhould they be legally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted
for the ſame; and thereupon to adviſe them
timely to repent of, and deſiſt from ſuch high <hi>Treaſonable
Attempts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. To clear both my ſelf and this my ſeaſonable <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
of our Fundamentall Lawes, Liberties, Government,</hi> from
the leaſt ſuſpition or ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dow of <hi>Faction, Sedition, Treaſon,</hi>
and <hi>Enmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> to the publick peace, weal, ſettlement of
the Nation, which thoſe, (and thoſe onely) who are
moſt Factious and ſeditious, and the greateſt Enemies,
Traytors to the publick tranquility, weal and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of our Kingdome, (as the premiſes evidence) will be
ready maliciouſly to aſperſe both me and it, with, as they
have done ſome other of my writings of this nature;
with all which, they muſt firſt brand Mr. <hi>St John</hi> Mr. <hi>Pym,</hi>
the whole <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> the laſt two, with all other
Parliamens forecited, ere they can accuſe, traduce, or
cenſure me, who do but barely relate, apply their words
and judgements without malice or partiality, for the
whole Kingdomes benefit and ſecurity.</p>
            <p>To theſe punctuall full Jury of Records and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary
Authorities in point, I could accumulate Sir
<hi>Edward Cook</hi> his 3. Inſtitutes, p. 9. printed and authoriſed
by the Houſe of Commons ſpeciall Order, the laſt Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament:
The ſeverall Speeches of Mr. <hi>Hide,</hi> Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi>
Mr. <hi>Pierpoint</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hollis, July</hi> 6. 1641. at the Lords
Bar in Parliament, by order of the Commons Houſe, at
the <hi>Impeachment of the Shipmony Judges of High Treaſon,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:118951:26"/>
printed in <hi>Diurnall Occurrences, and ſpeeches in Parliament,</hi>
London 1641. p. 237. to 264. Mr. <hi>Samuel Browns</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
at Law before the Lords and Commons at <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi>
Attainder; all manifeſting, their endevouring to
ſubvert the Fundamentall Laws and government of the
Nation to be <hi>HIGH TREASON;</hi> with ſundry other
printed Authorities to prove, <hi>That we have fundamentall
Laws, Liberties, Rights, and a fundamentall Government
likewiſe, which ought not to be innovated, violated, or ſubvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
upon any pretences whatſoever, by any power or prevailing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
But to avoid prolixity, (the double <hi>Jury</hi> of irrefra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable
and punctuall Authorities already produced, being
ſufficient to ſatisfie the moſt obſtinate Oppoſites formerly
contradicting it) I ſhall onely adde three ſwaying Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities
more, wherewith I ſhall conclude this point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt is a very late one, in a Treatiſe intituled,</hi> A
true State of the Common wealth of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and
<hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions thereunto belonging, in Reference
to the late eſtabliſhed Government, by a Lord Protector and a
<hi>PARLIAMENT. It being the Judgement of DIVERS
PERSONS,</hi> who throughout theſe late troubles, have <hi>appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi>
themſelves faithfull to the Cauſe and intereſt of God, and
their <hi>COUNTRY:</hi> preſented to the Publick, for the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of others. <hi>Printed at</hi> London 1654. <hi>who relating the
miſcarriages of the laſt</hi> Aſſembly at Weſtminſter, <hi>uſe theſe
expreſſions of them, p,</hi> 13, 14, 16, 17, 21, 22. But on the
contrary, it ſo fell out in a ſhort time, that there appeared many
in this Aſſembly of very contrary Principles to the intereſt afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid,
which led them violently on to attempt and promote many
things, the conſequence whereof would have been: <hi>A Subvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of the fundamentall Laws of the Land, the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
of Property, and an utter extinguiſhment of the
Goſpel.</hi> In truth their Principles led them <hi>TO A PUL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LING
DOWN ALL? AND ESTABLISHING NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THING.</hi>
So that inſtead of the expected ſettlement, they were
running <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut into <hi>FURTHER ANARCHY and CONFU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SION.</hi>
As to the Laws and Civil Rights of the Nation, nothing
would ſerve them, but <hi>A TOTALL ERADICATION OF
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118951:27"/>
THE OLD, and INTRODUCTION OF A NEW: and
ſo the</hi> Good, Old Laws of <hi>England,</hi> (the Guardians of our
Lives and Fortunes) <hi>eſtabliſhed with prudence, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
by the experience of many Ages and Generations:</hi>
(The Preſervation whereof, was a principall Ground of our late
Quarrel with the King) <hi>having been once aboliſhed, what
could we have expected afterward,</hi> but <hi>an inthroning
of Arbitrary Power in the Seat of Judicature, and an
expoſing of our Lives, our Eſtates, our Liberties,</hi> and <hi>all
that is dear unto us, as a Sacrifice to the boundleſſe Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite
of Meer Will and Power,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Things being at this Paſſe, and the Houſe (through theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings)
perfectly disjointed, it was in vain to look for a ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of this Nation from them, thus conſtituted on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
nothing elſe could be expected,</hi> But that the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
ſhould ſink under their Hands, <hi>and the great cauſe
hitherto ſo happily upheld and maintained, to be for ever loſt,
through their prepoſterous management of theſe affairs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
they had been intruſted.</hi> Whereupon they juſtifie their
diſſolution, and turning them forcibly out of doores
by the <hi>Souldiers,</hi> with ſhame and infamy; to prevent that
deſtruction which thereby was coming on <hi>THE WHOLE
LAND,</hi> but this New <hi>Powder Treaſon</hi> Plot, ſet on foot by
the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> to deſtroy our Laws, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
properties, Miniſters, and Religion it ſelf, at one
blow, and that in the very <hi>Parliament Houſe,</hi> where they
had been conſtantly defended, vindicated, preſerved, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed
in all former ages <hi>by all true Engliſh Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond is,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">See my Speech in Parliament. p. 100. to 108.</note> 
               <hi>The</hi> Votes of the Houſe of Commons,
<hi>concerning a Paper preſented to them, entituled</hi> An a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement
of the people for a firm and preſent peace, upon grounds
of Common Right 9. <hi>November,</hi> 1647. viz.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved upon the Queſtion, That the matters contained in
theſe Papers,</hi> Are deſtructive to the being of Parliaments,
and to the Fundamentall Government of this Kingdome,</p>
            <p>Reſolved, &amp;c. That a Letter be ſent to the Generall and
thoſe Papers incloſed, together with the Vote of this Houſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
them; And that he be deſired to examine the proceedings of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:118951:27"/>
this buſineſſe in the Army (<hi>where it was firſt coined</hi>) and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
an Accompt hereof to this Houſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe Votes were ſeconded ſoon after with theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing
votes, entred in the <hi>Commons Journall,</hi> and printed
by their <hi>ſpecial Order,</hi> 23. November, 1647.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Petition</hi> directed to the Supream Authority of
<hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Commons in Parliament</hi> aſſembled, <hi>The hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
petition of many Free born people of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was
read the firſt and ſecond time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved upon the Queſtion,</hi> that this petition is, <hi>A ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi>
and <hi>contemptuous avowing</hi> and proſecution of a former
petition and paper annexed, ſtiled, an agreement of the
people formerly <hi>adjudged by this Houſe, to be Deſtructive to
the being of Parliaments</hi> and <hi>Fundamentall Government of the
Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That</hi> Thomas Prince <hi>Cheeſemonger, and</hi>
Samuel Chidley, <hi>be forthwith committed</hi> priſoners <hi>to the
Priſon of the</hi> Gatehouſe, <hi>there to remain priſoners during
the pleaſure of</hi> this Houſe, <hi>for</hi> a Seditious avowing and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
<hi>of a former</hi> Petition, <hi>and Paper annexed, ſtiled,</hi> An
Agreement of the People, <hi>formerly</hi> Ajudged by this Houſe to be
deſtructive to the being of Parliamen's <hi>and</hi> fundamentall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Reſolved <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That <hi>Jeremy Jues, Thomas Taylor</hi> and
<hi>William Larnar,</hi> be forthwith committed to the Priſon of
<hi>Newgate,</hi> there to remain <hi>Priſoners,</hi> during the pleaſure
of this <hi>Houſe,</hi> for a <hi>ſeditious and contemptuous avowing</hi> and
<hi>proſecution</hi> of a former Petition and Paper annexed, ſtiled,
<hi>An Agrement of the people, formerly adjudged by this Houſe,</hi> to
be deſtructive to the being of Parliaments <hi>and</hi> Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
Government of this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Reſolved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That a Letter be prepared and ſent to
the Generall; taking notice of his proceeding in the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
(according to the Rules of <hi>Warre</hi>) of a <hi>muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
perſon</hi> (avowing and proſecuting this agreement in
the Army contrary to theſe Votes) at the Rendezvouz
near <hi>Ware;</hi> and to <hi>give him thanks for it:</hi> and to deſire
him to proſecute <hi>that Buſineſſe to the bottome;</hi> and to <hi>bring</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:118951:28"/>
Such guilty perſons as he ſhall think fit, to condigne
and exemplary Puniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved,</hi> &amp;c. That the Votes upon the Petition and Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
annexed, and likewiſe the Votes upon this Petition be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
printed and publiſhed.</p>
            <p>After which by a <hi>Speciall Ordinance of both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi>
17 December, 1647. No perſon whatſoever,
who had contrived, plotted, proſecuted or entred into
that Engagement intituled The agreement of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
declared <hi>To be deſtructive to the being of Parliaments,</hi> and
<hi>Fundamentall Government of the Kingdome,</hi> for one whole
year, was to be elected, choſen or put into the office or
Place of Lord <hi>Mayor or Alderman, Sheriffe, Deputy of a
Ward,</hi> or <hi>Common-Councel man of the City of</hi> London; <hi>or
to have a voice in the Election of any ſuch Officer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe particulars, with the Capitall Proceedings
againſt <hi>White</hi> and others who ſomented this <hi>Agreement in
the Army,</hi> abundantly evidence the veriey of my foreſaid
<hi>Propoſition,</hi> and the extraordinary guilt of thoſe Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
and Souldiers, who contrary to their <hi>own Votes, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,
Proceedings and Cenſures of others,</hi> have ſince proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted
this, the like, or far worſe <hi>Agreement,</hi> to the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
of our ancient Parliaments and their Priviledges,
and the fundamentall Government, Laws and Liberty of
our Nation, which I wiſh they would now ſadly lay to
heart.</p>
            <p>The third is the memorable Statutes of 3. <hi>Jacobi</hi> ch. 1,
2, 4, and 5. Which relating the old <hi>Gunpowder Treaſon
of the Jeſuites and Papiſts, and their infernal, inhumane, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous,
deteſtable plot, to blow up the King, Queen, Prince, Lords,
Commons, and whole Houſe of Peers with Gunpowder, when
they ſhould have been aſſembled in Parliament, in the upper
Houſe of Parliament, upon the fifth of</hi> November, <hi>in the year
of our Lord</hi> 1605, do aggravate the hainouſneſſe and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendency
thereof by this circumſtance, <hi>That it was (as
ſome of the principall Conſpirators thereof confeſſed) purpoſely
deviſed and concluded to be done in the ſaid Houſe,</hi> That where
ſundry neceſſary <hi>and</hi> Religious Laws for Preſervation of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:118951:28"/>
the Church <hi>and</hi> State were made, (<hi>which they falſely and
ſlanderouſly term, Cruel Laws enacted againſt them and their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi>)
Both Place and Perſons ſhould be all deſtroyed <hi>and</hi>
blown up at once: And by theſe dangerous conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
if it had not been miraculouſly prevented, but taken
effect. That it would have turned to the utter ruine,
overthrow and Subverſion <hi>Of the whole State and Common-Wealth
of this flouriſhing and renowned Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>Gods true
Religion therein eſtabliſhed by Law,</hi> and of our Laws and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.
For which horrid Treaſon, they <hi>were all at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted,
and then executed as Traytors, and ſome of their heads,
Quarters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Speeds History, p. 1250 and Mr. John Vica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'s Hiſtory of the Gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Treaſon, and the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment of Traytors.</note> 
               <hi>ſet up upon the Parliament Houſe for terrour of others.</hi>
Even ſo let all other Traytors, Conſpirators againſt our
Fundamental Laws, Liberties, Government, Kings, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
and Religion, treading preſumptuouſly in their
Jeſuiticall footſteps,<note n="a" place="margin">Judges 5. 31</note> 
               <hi>periſh O Lord, but let all them who
cordially love,</hi> and ſtrenuouſly maintain them againſt all
Conſpirators, Traytors, Underminers, Invaders what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,
<hi>be as the Sunne when he goeth forth in his might: That
the Land may have reſt,</hi> peace, Settlement again, for as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
years at leaſt, as it had before our late innovations,
Warres, Confuſions, <hi>by their reſtitution and eſtabliſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:118951:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HAving thus ſufficiently proved,</hi> That the Kingdome,
and Freemen of <hi>England,</hi> have ſome ancient, hereditary
Rights, Liberties, Franchiſes, Priviledges, Cuſtomes, properly
called F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDAMENTALL, as likewiſe a Fundamentall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
no wayes to be altered, undermined, ſubverted, direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
or indirectly, under the guilt and pain of High Treaſon in
thoſe who attempt it; eſpecially by Fraud, Force, or armed
Power.</p>
               <p>I ſhall in the ſecond place preſent you in brief Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
a <hi>Summary</hi> of the chiefeſt and moſt conſiderable of
them, which our prudent Anceſtors in former ages, and
our lateſt reall Parliaments, have both declared to be,
and eagerly conteſted for, as <hi>Fundamentall</hi> and Eſſentiall
to their very <hi>being</hi> and <hi>well being,</hi> as a <hi>Free people, Kingdome,
Republick,</hi> unwilling to be enſlaved under any <hi>yokes</hi> of
Tyranny or arbitrary power, that ſo the whole Nation
may the more perſpicuouſly know and diſcern them, the
more ſtrenuouſly contend for them, the more vigilantly
watch againſt their violations, underminings in any
kind, by any Powers, or Pretences whatſoever; and
tranſmit, perpetuate them intirely to their poſterities, as
their beſt and chiefeſt inheritance.</p>
               <p>I ſhall compriſe the <hi>Summe</hi> and Subſtance of them all
in theſe 9. Propoſitions; beginning with the Subjects
Property, which hath been more frequently, univerſally
invaded, aſſaulted, undermined by our Kings, and their
evill inſtruments; and thereupon more ſtrenuouſly, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
and vigilantly maintained, retained by our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,
Parliaments and the people in all ages (till of late
years) than any or all of the reſt put together, though
every of them have been conſtantly defended, maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
when impugned, or incroached upon by our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors
and our ſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:118951:29"/>
1. That no Tax, Tallage, Aid, Subſidy, Cuſtome,
Contribution, Loan, Impoſition, Exciſe or other Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſement
whatſoever, for Defence of the Realm by Land
or Sea, or any other publick ordinary, or extraordinary
occaſion, may or ought to be impoſed, or levyed upon
all or any of the Freemen of <hi>England,</hi> by reaſon of any
pretended or reall Danger, Neceſſity or other pretext;
by the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> or any other Powers, but onely
with and by their common conſent and Grant, in a free
and lawfull Parliament duly ſummoned and elected:
Except onely ſuch ancient, legall Ayds, as they are ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
obliged to render by their Tenures, Charters,
Contracts, and the Common Law of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. That no Freeman of <hi>England</hi> ought to be arreſted,
confined, impriſoned, in any private Caſtles, or remote,
unuſuall Priſons under Souldiers or other Guardians,
but onely in uſuall or Common Gaols, under ſworn,
reſponſible Gaolers, in the County where he lives, or is
apprehended, and where his Friends may freely viſit and
relieve him with neceſſaries: And that onely for ſome juſt,
and legall cauſe expreſſed in the Writ, Warrant, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe,
by which he is arreſted, or impriſoned; which ought
to be legally executed by known, legal, reſponſible
ſworn Officers of Juſtice, not unknown military Officers,
Troopers, or other illegall Catchpols, That no ſuch
Freeman ought to be denied bail, Mainpriſe, or the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit
of an <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> or any other Legal Writ for his
enlargement, when bailable or incumpernable by Law;
nor to be detained priſoner for any reall or pretended
Crime, not bailable by Law, then untill the next Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
or Speciall Gaol-delivery, held in the County where
he is impriſoned; where he ought to be legally tried and
proceeded againſt, or elſe enlarged by the Juſtices, without
deniall or delay of Right and Juſtice. And that no ſuch
Freeman may or ought to be outlawed, exiled, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
to any kind of corporall puniſhment, loſſe of Life or
Member, or otherwiſe deſtroyed or paſſed upon, but
onely by due and lawfull Proceſſe, Indictment, and the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118951:30"/>
lawfull Triall, Verdict and Judgement of his Peers, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the good old Law of the Land, in ſome uſuall
Court of Publick Juſtice: not by and in new illegall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary,
or other Arbitrary Judicatories, Committees, or
Courts of High Juſtice, unknown to our Anceſtors.</p>
               <p>3. That no Freeman of <hi>England,</hi> unleſſe it be by Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
Grant and Act of Parliament may or ought to be
compelled, enforced, preſſed or arrayed to go forth of
his own Countrey (much leſſe out of the Realm into
forreign parts) againſt his will in times of Warre or
Peace, or except he be ſpecially obliged thereto by anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
Tenures and Charters; ſave onely upon the ſudden
coming of ſtrange enemies into the Realm, and then he
is to array himſelf onely in ſuch ſort, as he is bound to
do by the ancient Laws and Cuſtomes of the Kingdome
ſtill in force.</p>
               <p>4. That no Freeman of <hi>England,</hi> may or ought to be
disinherited, diſſeiſed, diſpoſſeſſed or deprived of any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance,
Freehold, Liberty, Cuſtome, Franchiſe, Chattle,
Goods whatſoever without his own Gift, Grant, or
free Conſent, unleſſe it be by lawfull Proceſſe, Triall and
Judgement of his Peers, or ſpecial Grant by act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>5. That the old received Government, Lawes, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,
Cuſtomes, Priviledges, Courts of Juſtice, legal
Proceſſe of the Kingdome and Crown ought not to be
altered, repealed, ſuppreſſed, nor any new form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
Law, Statute, Ordinance Court of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
Writs, or legal Proceedings inſtituted or impoſed
on all or any of the Free-men of <hi>England,</hi> by any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
or Perſons, but onely in and by the Kingdomes free
and full conſent in a lawfull Parliament, wherein the
Legiſlative Power ſolely reſides.</p>
               <p>6. That Parliaments ought to be duly ſummoned, and
held for the good and ſafety of the Kingdome every year,
or every three years at leaſt, or ſo often as there is juſt
occaſion. That the Election of all Knights, Citizens and
Burgeſſes, to ſit and ſerve in Parliament (and ſo of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:118951:30"/>
Elective Officers) ought to be free. That all Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
of Parliament hereditary or Elective, ought to be
preſent, and there freely to ſpeak and vote according to
their judgements and Conſciences, without any over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awing
Guards to terrifie them; and none to be forced or
ſecluded thence. And that all Parliaments not thus duly
ſummoned, elected whilſt held, but unduly packed, and
all Acts of Parliament fraudulently and forcibly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured
by indirect means, ought to be nulled, repealed,
as void, and of dangerous preſident.</p>
               <p>7. That neither the Kings nor any Subjects of the
Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> may or ought to be ſummoned
before any Forreign Powers or Jurisdictions whatſoever,
out of the Realm, or within the ſame, for any manner
of Right, Inheritance, Thing belonging to them, or
Offence done by them within the Realm.</p>
               <p>8. That all Subjects of the Realm are obliged by Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance
and duty to defend their Lawfull Kings, Perſons,
Crowns, the Laws, Rights and Priviledges of the Realm,
and of Parliament againſt all Uſurpers, Traytors, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,
and Conſpiracies. And that no Subject of this
Realm, who according to his duty, and Allegiance ſhall
ſerve his King in his Warres, for the juſt defence of him
and the Land, againſt Forreign enemies or Rebels, ſhall
loſe or forfeit any thing for doing his true duty, ſervice,
and Allegiance to him therein; but utterly diſcharged
of all vexation, trouble, or loſſe.</p>
               <p>9. That no publick Warre by Land or Sea ought to
be made or levied with or againſt any Forreign Nation,
or Publick Truce or League entred into with Forreign
Realms or States, to bind the Nation, without their
Common advice and conſent in Parliament.</p>
               <p>10. That the ancient, Honours, Manors, Lands, Rents,
Revenues, Inheritances, Right, and perquiſites of the
Crown of <hi>England,</hi> originally ſettled thereon for the
Eaſe &amp; Exemption of the people from all kind of Taxes,
payments whatſoever (unleſſe in caſes of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
neceſſity) and for defraying all the conſtant, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:118951:31"/>
expences of the Kingdome, (as the expences of the
Kings houſhold, Court, Officers, Judges, Embaſſadors,
Gariſons, Navy and the like) ought not to be ſold, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enated,
given away or granted from it, to the prejudice
of the Crown and burdening of the people. And that all
Sales, Alienations, Gifts, or Grants thereof, to the empair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of the publick Revenue, or prejudice of the Crown
and people, are void in Law, and ought to be reſumed, and
repealed, by our Parliaments and Kings, as they have
frequently been in all former ages.</p>
               <p>For the Readers fuller ſatisfaction in each of theſe
propoſitions (ſome of which I muſt ſhew here but briefly,
touch for brevity ſake, having elſewhere fully debated
them in print) I ſhall ſpecially recommend unto him the
peruſall of ſuch Tractates, and Arguments formerly
publiſhed, wherein each of them hath been fully diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
which he may peruſe at his beſt leaſure.</p>
               <p>The firſt of theſe Fundamentalls (which I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntend prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally
to infiſt on) is fully aſſerted, debated, confirmed
by 13. H. 4. f. 14. By <hi>Forteſcue</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice, and
Chancellour of <hi>England, de laudibus Legum Angliae,</hi> dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
by him to King <hi>Henry</hi> the 6. f. 25. c. 36. f. 84. By a <hi>learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and neceſſary Argument againſt impoſitions in Parliament,</hi> of
7. <hi>Jacobi:</hi> by a late <hi>Reverend Judge,</hi> printed at <hi>London</hi> 1641.
By Mr. <hi>William Hakewell, in his Liberty of the Subject againſt
Impoſitions,</hi> maintained in an <hi>Argument</hi> in the <hi>Parliament</hi>
of 7. <hi>Jacobi:</hi> printed at <hi>London</hi> 1641. By <hi>Judge Crooks, and
Judge Huttons Arguments</hi> concerning <hi>Shipmony</hi> both print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
at <hi>London</hi> 1641. By the <hi>Caſe of Shipmony</hi> briefly <hi>diſcuſſed
London,</hi> 1640. by Mr. <hi>St. Johns Argument, and Speech againſt
Shipmony,</hi> printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1641. By Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> in
his 1. Inſtitutes, p. 46. and 57. to 64. and 528. to 537. By
the 1. and 2. <hi>Remonſtrance of the Lords and Commons in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
againſt the Commiſſion of Array.</hi> Exact Collection
p. 386. to 398. and 850. to 890. and by my own <hi>Humble
Remonſtrance againſt Shipmony,</hi> London, 1643. <hi>The fourth
part of the Soveraign power of Parliaments and Kingdomes,</hi> p. 14.
to 26. and my Legall Vindications of the Liberties of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:118951:31"/>
                  <hi>England</hi> againſt Illegall Taxes, <hi>&amp;c. London</hi> 1649. and by
the Records and Statutes cited in the enſuing Chapter, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring
for the moſt part to the firſt Propoſition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond, third, and fourth of them are largely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated
and confirmed by a</hi> Conference deſired by the Lords, and
had by a Committee of both Houſes, concerning the Rights and
Priviledges of the Subject, 3. Aprilis, 4. Caroli <hi>printed at</hi>
London 1642. <hi>By Sir</hi> Edward Cook <hi>in his</hi> Inſtitutes <hi>on</hi> Magna
Charta. <hi>c. 29. p. 45. to 57. By the 1. and</hi> 2. Remonſtrance of
the Lords and Commons againſt the Commiſſion of Array, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act
Collection p.</hi> 386. &amp;c. 850. <hi>to 890. By</hi> Judge Crooks,
and Judge Huttons Arguments againſt Shipmony: <hi>By Sir</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert
Cotton <hi>his</hi> Poſthuma <hi>p. 222. to 269. By my</hi> Breviate of
the Prelates encroachments on the Kings Prerogative, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
Liberties. <hi>p.</hi> 138. &amp;c. My new diſcovery of the Prelates ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny,
<hi>p. 137. to 183. and ſome of the enſuing Statutes,
and Records.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fifth and ſixth of them are fully cleared and vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
in and by the Prologues of all our Councils, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,
Laws, before and ſince the Conqueſt. By Sir</hi> Edward
Cooks 4. <hi>Inſtitutes. ch. 1. Mr.</hi> Cromptons <hi>Jurisdiction of
Courts. Title,</hi> High Court of Parliament: <hi>My</hi> Soveraign
power of Parliaments and Kingdomes, <hi>p. 1, 2, 3, 4. My</hi> Legal
Vindication againſt illegal Taxes, <hi>and</hi> pretended Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
London 1649<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Prynne the Member, reconciled to Prynne
the Barreſter, <hi>printed the ſame year. My</hi> Hiſtoricall Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
of the ancient great Councils of the Parliaments of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
London 1649. <hi>My</hi> Truth triumphing over Falſhood, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity
over Novelty. London 1645. <hi>and ſome of the Records
hereafter tranſcribed. In this I ſhall be more ſparing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
ſo fully confirmed in theſe and other Treatiſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſeventh is ratified by Sir <hi>Edward Cooks</hi> 1. Inſtitutes,
p. 97, 98. 4. Inſtitutes p. 89. and 5. Report <hi>Cawdries</hi> Caſe
of the Kings Eccleſiaſticall Lawes: and <hi>Raſtals</hi> Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of Statutes. Tit. <hi>Proviſors, Praemunire</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi>
11. H. 7. c. 1. and other Records and Statutes in the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Chapter.</p>
               <p>The eighth and ninth are fully debated in my <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:118951:32"/>
Power of Parliaments and Kingdomes,</hi> Part. 2. p. 3. to.
34. Part fourth, p. 162. to 170. and touched in Sir <hi>Robert
Cottons Poſthuma</hi> p. 174. 179.</p>
               <p>How all and every of theſe Fundamentall Liberties,
Rights, Franchiſes, Lawes, have been unparalelledly
violated, ſubverted, in all and every particular of late
years beyond all Preſidents in the worſt of former ages,
even by their greateſt pretended <hi>Propugners;</hi> their own
printed <hi>Edicts, Inſtruments, Ordinances, Papers,</hi> together
with their illegall oppreſſions, Taxes, Exciſes, Impoſts,
Rapines, violences, Proceedings of all kinds, (whereof
I ſhall give a brief accompt in its due place) will ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
evidence, if compared with the premiſed <hi>propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
Which abundantly confirm the truth of our <hi>Saviours</hi>
words, <hi>John</hi> 10. 1. 10. and this rule of <hi>Johannis Angelius,
Wenderhagen: Politicae Synopticae. lib. 3. c. 9. ſect. 11. p.</hi> 310.
<hi>Hinc Regulae loco notandum,</hi> Quod omne Regnum Vi Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata
acquiſitum in Effectu Subditis Semper in durioris
Servitutis conditiones arripiat, <hi>licet à principio</hi> Ducedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem
prurientibus ſpirare videatur. <hi>Ideo cunctis hoc caven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi>
Nè temerè ſe duci patiantur.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:118951:32"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
